<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/">
<channel>
	<title>Game Boy Essentials</title>
	<description>A project to review and talk about the essential games you must play on Game Boy to understand its appeal and its success. Not only the best games for the system, but also the bad games that enlighten the legacy of the most popular video game console of the 1990s.</description>		
	<link>http://localhost:4000</link>
	<atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<item>
		<title>Game Boy Camera</title>
		<description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;game-boy-camera&quot;&gt;Game Boy Camera&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Japanese release in February 1998&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;North American release in May 1998&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;European release in 1998&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Published by Nintendo&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Developed by Nintendo R&amp;amp;D1&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;boxart&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/mgb-006/mgb-006-1.jpg&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;712&quot; alt=&quot;You might laugh now, but for a short time, this thing was impressive.&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;p&gt;You might laugh now, but for a short time, this thing was impressive.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-camera-in-your-pocket&quot;&gt;A Camera in Your Pocket&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;gb float left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/mgb-006/mgb-006-2.png&quot; width=&quot;480&quot; height=&quot;432&quot; alt=&quot;Game Boy Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where is the closest camera you own right now? In your pockets? If you’re reading this on your phone, you have a camera looking at you right now, and a whole family of high-quality sensors on the back of the very device with which you’re reading this article. The ubiquity of cameras has thoroughly changed our society, from personal communications to police oversight. The Game Boy Camera came out at a time well before that revolution when a photograph was still an event. The closest peer to this accessory in terms of size and price in 1998 were disposable cameras. &lt;a href=&quot;https://tedium.co/2018/07/26/disposable-camera-history/&quot;&gt;Costing $10 or lower&lt;/a&gt;, disposable cameras were a democratizing force for the camera world. They allowed you to enjoy photography for a very small initial investment. However, they did not change the fundamentals of film cameras; you needed to pay for film development for all the pictures you took, even for duds you were going to throw away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Digital cameras were already available in 1998. With their rewritable media, they allowed you to take and delete an infinite number of pictures. You were limited only by your digital storage space. In 1998 most cameras saved their pictures on 3 &amp;amp; 1/2-inch diskettes, which meant you could carry a stack of them with you. However, the Sony Mavicas sold for around USD $800 at that time; an expensive sum for very low-resolution pictures. The Game Boy Camera is a peer of those early digital cameras. It was unique amongst digital cameras for its very low price, which came with absurd limitations that severely limited its appeal. We’ll discuss this fascinating Nintendo device in detail, and together we’ll discover what motivated the employees at Nintendo to make the Game Boy Camera.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-greyscale-camera&quot;&gt;A Greyscale Camera&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;When Yokoi Gunpei left Nintendo, Hirokazu Tanaka felt betrayed by his departure, and wanted to prove that people at Nintendo could still apply his lessons to create inventive products. The Game Boy Camera and its printer were born of this desire to show the creativity of the developers who stayed with Nintendo. Yokoi accidentally died before the camera was released, and his thanked in the credits.&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;—Translated from &lt;em&gt;L’histoire de Nintendo Volume 4&lt;/em&gt;, P. 153.&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yokoi Gunpei is best remembered as the father of the Game Boy, since he was the leader of R&amp;amp;D1 where the device was developed. When Yokoi left Nintendo in the mid ’90s, Hirokazu &lt;em&gt;Hip&lt;/em&gt; Tanaka, a music composer inside the company, saw the Game Boy Camera project as a way to prove his and his colleagues’ worth. They had the engineers to develop future iterations of the Game Boy, but they had lost their superstar toymaker. Yokoi was famous for his work at Nintendo; a rare privilege only bestowed back then upon him and Miyamoto. Miyamoto was a video game developer but Yokoi was something else entirely. He was an engineer and an inveterate tinkerer. Ultimately, he was Nintendo’s star toymaker. Yokoi had started at Nintendo when it was still a playing card company, and his wonderful designs gave Nintendo a solid footing when it diverted in toymaking. The stories around Yokoi’s mechanical creations were legend. With Yokoi’s departure, the R&amp;amp;D1 division was further divided into a hardware and a software section. Okada Satoru was put in charge of the hardware, and no one internally could doubt his ability to deliver good products, since he was the person who defined all the important details of the Game Boy. An engineer who started at R&amp;amp;D1 working for Yokoi, he went against his boss during the Game Boy’s development. Yokoi wanted the Game Boy to be similar to a Game &amp;amp; Watch that would be popular for a &lt;em&gt;season&lt;/em&gt;. Perhaps a machine that could only play a limited set of predetermined games. Yokoi had the mentality of a toy-maker; he focused on building toys that would grab children’s attention for a moment before they moved on to something else. It was Okada that wanted a hardware platform that developers could fully program. Something where our waning attention is focused on the cartridges, not on the hardware. Simply put, a portable Famicom. Yokoi relented and let Okada build the Game Boy his way. This highlights the trustworthiness and competence of Okada; he would continue to deliver portable success after portable success until his retirement from Nintendo in 2012. Back in 1998, he had not yet proven himself, and was certainly not known for his toymaker mentality. Making a digital camera for the Game Boy might prove that Nintendo R&amp;amp;D1 could still make interesting toy-like accessories without Yokoi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;limited-hardware&quot;&gt;Limited Hardware&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With our modern point of view, &lt;em&gt;Game Boy Camera&lt;/em&gt; is a complete joke. It can seem like no one could tolerate its low image quality and that it must have been a monumental flop. The reality is far from that. Looking back at the &lt;em&gt;Game Boy Camera&lt;/em&gt;’s release in 1998, the device enjoyed a somewhat warm reception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;gallery-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;art gallery&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/mgb-006/mgb-006-3.png&quot; width=&quot;612&quot; height=&quot;1270&quot; alt=&quot;[Popular Science, July 1998, p. 12](https://books.google.ca/books?id=3Bxy4y0umo0C&amp;amp;pg=PA12)&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.ca/books?id=3Bxy4y0umo0C&amp;amp;pg=PA12&quot;&gt;Popular Science, July 1998, p. 12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;art gallery&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/mgb-006/mgb-006-4.png&quot; width=&quot;1812&quot; height=&quot;1178&quot; alt=&quot;[Boys’ Life, September 1998, p. 11](https://books.google.ca/books?id=Nv8DAAAAMBAJ&amp;amp;pg=PA11)&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.ca/books?id=Nv8DAAAAMBAJ&amp;amp;pg=PA11&quot;&gt;Boys’ Life, September 1998, p. 11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;art gallery&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/mgb-006/mgb-006-5.png&quot; width=&quot;1630&quot; height=&quot;612&quot; alt=&quot;[Vibe, August 1998, p. 148](https://archive.org/details/bub_gb_JywEAAAAMBAJ/page/n157/mode/2up)&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/bub_gb_JywEAAAAMBAJ/page/n157/mode/2up&quot;&gt;Vibe, August 1998, p. 148&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;art gallery&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/mgb-006/mgb-006-6.png&quot; width=&quot;950&quot; height=&quot;1232&quot; alt=&quot;[GamePro, August 1998, p. 30](https://archive.org/details/GamePro_Issue_109_August_1998/page/n31/mode/2up)&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/GamePro_Issue_109_August_1998/page/n31/mode/2up&quot;&gt;GamePro, August 1998, p. 30&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, the pictures it takes are laughably bad, with a ridiculously low 128 by 112-pixel resolution. The thing is only good at taking pictures of large things (like a head or a dog) from way up close. Don’t even try to take a picture of a distant landscape view. To top off the mediocrity, pictures have no colour, being only available in the same four shades as your Game Boy. However, you have to look at what digital cameras were capable of doing and at what price to understand the device’s appeal in 1998. Of course, something like the &lt;a href=&quot;https://global.canon/en/c-museum/product/dslr777.html&quot;&gt;Canon EOS D2000&lt;/a&gt; existed, but this 1728 by 1152 resolution professional device retailed for over $15,000 USD. It was also a bleeding edge trailblazer; it was the first digital camera somewhat respected by professionals. We have to look downmarket to find peers of our little puny &lt;em&gt;Game Boy Camera&lt;/em&gt;. For example, Minton made a crappy OEM camera that was re-badged by countless companies. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.digitalkameramuseum.de/en/cameras/item/jenoptik-jd11-entrance&quot;&gt;It came with a 640 x 480 pixel sensor and sold for around $149 USD&lt;/a&gt;. It’s a much better device at three times the price but it is still a terrible camera compared to modern standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you look at it, the Game Boy Camera is more akin to a toy than a digital camera. We’re lucky, we have a new camera toy from 1998 to compare it against.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;art&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/mgb-006/mgb-006-7.jpg&quot; width=&quot;1000&quot; height=&quot;669&quot; alt=&quot;BarbieCam!&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;p&gt;BarbieCam!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Barbie Photo Designer&lt;/em&gt; was announced in September of 1998, obviously for the upcoming Holiday season and was a package consisting of the digital camera and its accompanying PC software. It retailed for $69.99, a shockingly low price at first glance for a digital camera and PC software. Upon closer examination the device is not too good to be true. Although it took colour photos, it is very close to the Game Boy Camera in terms of resolution: 160 by 120 pixels. That’s minuscule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;art&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/mgb-006/mgb-006-8.jpg&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;480&quot; alt=&quot;An example of a BarbieCam photo. This photo was taken with the later Nickelodeon model, which is the same camera. Photo courtesy of [Superkids.com](https://www.superkids.com/aweb/pages/reviews/camera/1/nick/merge.shtml).&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;p&gt;An example of a BarbieCam photo. This photo was taken with the later Nickelodeon model, which is the same camera. Photo courtesy of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.superkids.com/aweb/pages/reviews/camera/1/nick/merge.shtml&quot;&gt;Superkids.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a severely limited device. It’s a digital camera but it doesn’t have a screen or removable media. All the beautiful benefits of digital photography come from those two functionalities. Without a screen you can’t know if the picture you took is any good and without removable media you can’t keep taking pictures by swapping SD cards or whatnot. You’re stuck with the six pictures it can keep in its internal memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The device’s only options are taking pictures or deleting all the meagre six pictures without ever looking at them. Once you connect to a PC, you can very slowly transfer your pictures and finally see them for the first time. I imagine most kids ended up using the device in their home fairly close to their PC due to those extreme limitations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving on to the software, both companies chose to focus on offering games with the pictures you took to complement their low-resolution cameras. I guess there aren’t many ways to make a bad quality camera &lt;em&gt;fun&lt;/em&gt;. When you compare the disadvantages of &lt;em&gt;Barbie Photo Designer&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Game Boy Camera&lt;/em&gt;, that’s where you understand that the portability, viewfinder and memory for 30 pictures make the &lt;em&gt;Game Boy Camera&lt;/em&gt; a competitive package in this brand new toy camera category. This category was hotter than you think as well: &lt;em&gt;Barbie Photo Designer&lt;/em&gt; sold 300,000 copies in the US in its first year on the market and the &lt;em&gt;Game Boy Camera&lt;/em&gt; sold a million copies in Japan. However, the market would quickly get saturated with copycats, and by the mid-2000s digital cameras had come down in price enough that a toy digital camera seemingly became a niche item. Parents seemingly bought their kids full-fledged cameras instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;terrible-software&quot;&gt;Terrible Software&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll say it upfront; I don’t like the &lt;em&gt;Game Boy Camera&lt;/em&gt; software. It’s a mess. It features so many baffling interface decisions. People have called it quirky. I have a different word for it: bad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;art&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/mgb-006/mgb-006-9.png&quot; width=&quot;2100&quot; height=&quot;1488&quot; alt=&quot;[The Nintendo Game Boy Camera Funtography Guide provides a full map of the software](https://archive.org/details/nintendofuntographyguide/page/n5/mode/2up)&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/nintendofuntographyguide/page/n5/mode/2up&quot;&gt;The Nintendo Game Boy Camera Funtography Guide provides a full map of the software&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can immediately see that there are a lot of things you can do. Outside of &lt;em&gt;Mario Paint&lt;/em&gt;, I can’t think Nintendo had ever made a user interface this complex before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon starting the device, you’re presented with a start screen with photos of someone in a Mario costume. This shows one conceit of the software; that it will sometimes use real photos taken with a &lt;em&gt;Game Boy Camera&lt;/em&gt;. It’s not a full design choice. Large sections of the interface use drawn art to represent characters. If you get an idea like that, I’d expect them to use it fully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;gb float left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/mgb-006/mgb-006-10.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;Game Boy Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get a complete rookie mistake on the main screen of the interface: they never indicate you can press the Start button to access settings. So on a screen with three clearly written choices, you actually have four. Let’s jump into the worst segment of the device; Play. When you go into this segment, a game of &lt;em&gt;Space Fever II&lt;/em&gt; immediately begins. Two enemies drop down from the top of the screen, with letters written on them. Now, those enemies are actually the selection method for the &lt;strong&gt;other&lt;/strong&gt; games you can play. So if you shoot those lettered enemies, you start another completely different game. However, if you shoot none of them, or miss your shot, &lt;em&gt;Space Fever II&lt;/em&gt; will begin. Imagine that; a selection menu with a time limit. Upon starting those other games, you get astoundingly different screens to navigate their respective options. There is no general logic. The whole UI is a mad house.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;gallery-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;gb gallery&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/mgb-006/mgb-006-11.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;Game Boy Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;gb gallery&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/mgb-006/mgb-006-12.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;Game Boy Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;gb gallery&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/mgb-006/mgb-006-13.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;Game Boy Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first game is a copy of the first Game &amp;amp; Watch title, &lt;em&gt;Ball&lt;/em&gt;. We’ve discussed it previously when talking about &lt;a href=&quot;/articles/dmg-agga/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Game Boy Gallery&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. This version is using different sprites for the body, and allows you to use pictures for the face. The second game is a small DJ toy that I cannot understand for the life of me. The final game, which you unlock upon completing &lt;em&gt;Space Fever II&lt;/em&gt;, is a running game where you mash buttons. Once again, you can put your face on the character you play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;gb&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/mgb-006/mgb-006-14.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;The Shoot menu&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Shoot menu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon going to the Shoot segment, you get what is supposed to be a parody of an RPG’s battle screen, with pixel art of people standing in as your enemies. Since you just came from a screen where someone in a Mario suit was dancing about, the joke falls flat immediately. The battle screen includes a run command, leading to an infamous joke played on the user.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;gb&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/mgb-006/mgb-006-15.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;What are you running away from? BAD UI!&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;p&gt;What are you running away from? BAD UI!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That jokey screen is meant to tell the player that they can’t run away, this isn’t an RPG, just a parody of one. But the very real face has those hideous drawings added on them. It’s just so out of place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two most sedate and reasonable segments of the software are the viewfinder screens and the photo album under View. The picture taking features all the controls around the viewfinder, arranged in an intelligent manner that focuses on quick adjustments. The photo album navigation is pretty straightforward, and once you reach the single picture view, all the options are also arranged around the picture. If you dig deep enough, you can find drawing tools that provide you with a barebones &lt;em&gt;Mario Paint&lt;/em&gt;. You could take a picture of a white wall and just draw on your Game Boy. You don’t get the benefit of a mouse, but it’s a fun, well designed little drawing utility in a sea of terrible UI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;gallery-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;gb gallery&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/mgb-006/mgb-006-16.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;Game Boy Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;gb gallery&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/mgb-006/mgb-006-17.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;Game Boy Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;gb gallery&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/mgb-006/mgb-006-18.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;Game Boy Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;gb gallery&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/mgb-006/mgb-006-19.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;Game Boy Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;gb gallery&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/mgb-006/mgb-006-20.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;Game Boy Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;gb gallery&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/mgb-006/mgb-006-21.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;Game Boy Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The camera has far more tricks up its sleeve, and they are all bespoke tools that are hard to grasp because their user interface is not standardized. All in all I think part of the mess is explained by the number of companies who worked on the project. Employees from Creatures (formerly Ape), Game Freak, and R&amp;amp;D1 are all credited. This is a complete guess, but I think employees completed different segments of the software alone and those were added together with no regards for consistency. Even Jupiter, the company mostly known for Picross, is thanked in the credits but they might have supported in other ways like Quality Assurance. None of the craziness in the software was featured on the box; the box is very sedate, even in Japanese. The ads themselves, in both Japan and the US, focus heavily on the power of easy photography (duh) and the fun that can be had with the stamps implemented in the painting tools of the photo album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;gb float right&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/mgb-006/mgb-006-22.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;Game Boy Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We got a surprising revelation just recently in 2020 that highlights the poor user interface design. As a part of the &lt;em&gt;Gigaleak&lt;/em&gt;, a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nintendo_data_leak&quot;&gt;massive lotcheck of Game Boy titles was uncovered&lt;/a&gt;. Lotchecks, in internal Nintendo parlance, are lists of ROM ready for use in cartridges. They’re the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Software_release_life_cycle#RTM&quot;&gt;golden masters&lt;/a&gt;. Amongst this lotcheck was &lt;em&gt;Hello Kitty Pocket Camera&lt;/em&gt;, a special version of the camera dedicated to whom else but Hello Kitty. This whole special version of the Game Boy Camera is 100% complete, yet was &lt;strong&gt;never released&lt;/strong&gt;. No one outside Nintendo had seen this before 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have no information about what the hardware could have looked like, but we can be quite certain no important external changes were planned. Perhaps the camera would have been pink, with a Hello Kitty decal on it. &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/hello-kitty-pocket-camera-japan-rc-2&quot;&gt;It’s when you load up this golden master in an emulator&lt;/a&gt; that you see the changes. While all the camera functionality from the released version is present, nothing from the released Game Boy Camera user interface was reused. I’m not versed enough in Japanese to explore the interface in detail but my cursory look revealed a much improved UI. For example, if pressing Start sends you to another screen, you see a mention from the Hello Kitty UI. All the creepy pictures and inscrutable in-jokes have been removed. It’s clear the Hello Kitty UI was their second attempt at a &lt;em&gt;Game Boy Camera&lt;/em&gt; interface, and this second crack at the problem gave them enough time to finally make a workable interface. It’s just a shame they never released it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;gb&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/mgb-006/mgb-006-23.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;Game Boy Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;game-boy-camera-gets-a-receipt-printer&quot;&gt;Game Boy Camera Gets a Receipt Printer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nowadays, people are satisfied that their photos live online, but in 1998, everybody expected to get printed copies of every picture they took. You could trade pictures with another &lt;em&gt;Game Boy Camera&lt;/em&gt; using a Link Cable, but keeping your pictures imprisoned inside a &lt;em&gt;Game Boy Camera&lt;/em&gt; was a non-starter; Nintendo wanted to provide printing capabilities. While Nintendo could have answered with a stereotypically Japanese solution by putting printing kiosks in combinis all over Japan, leaving the rest of the world to fend for itself, they instead developed a portable printer one could easily buy alongside the camera. This was a great idea in practice, and a marked improvement over &lt;em&gt;Mario Paint&lt;/em&gt;. I feel like &lt;em&gt;Mario Paint&lt;/em&gt; never reach its full potential because it never had any print capabilities outside of &lt;em&gt;record your art on a VHS tape and figure something out from there&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;art&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/mgb-006/mgb-006-24.jpg&quot; width=&quot;2515&quot; height=&quot;3473&quot; alt=&quot;The Game Boy Printer&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Game Boy Printer&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So as with the camera came the Game Boy Printer. Connected through the link cable port, running with a whopping six AA batteries and &lt;a href=&quot;https://christmas.musetechnical.com/ShowCatalogPage/1998-JCPenney-Christmas-Book/0547&quot;&gt;retailing for the relatively high price of $60 upon release in 1998&lt;/a&gt;, the device uses thermal paper just like your receipt at the grocery store. Just like we discussed earlier with the camera, Nintendo knew they had to compensate for their bargain bin technology, so they wisely included thermal paper with a sticking back. This turned bad pictures into &lt;em&gt;collectable pictures&lt;/em&gt;. You could stick your pictures in a book, collect pictures of different plants or animals, stick pictures of people on their books, etc. Selling paper with a sticky back was a genius idea to compensate for a poor printing quality; and the printing quality was indeed bad. No one goes to a thermal printer for a beautiful, detailed print. It’s a cheap way to get something on paper fast. It will work fine for fun prints to share in the moment, but you’re not going to preserve your pictures long-term with those prints. Just like your receipts the prints fade with time. So if you have any old printed pictures from way back, they’ll be very faded now, due to the thermal paper technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Game Boy Printer enjoyed a life outside its release with the &lt;em&gt;Game Boy Camera&lt;/em&gt;. A few games included the ability to print some stuff; banners, high scores, medals. &lt;em&gt;Pokémon Yellow&lt;/em&gt; allowed you to print the content of your PC boxes for example, providing potential relief from all the box shuffling needed to manage your captured Pokémons. When I look at an &lt;a href=&quot;https://gamefaqs.gamespot.com/gameboy/916375-game-boy/faqs/35200&quot;&gt;exhaustive list of what can be printed&lt;/a&gt;, I find nothing impressive. Add the high price of the printer coupled with its large appetite for batteries and I feel like anyone who bought the printer was disappointed by its usage outside of &lt;em&gt;Game Boy Camera&lt;/em&gt;. I didn’t buy it, and still do not own one; when I bought my &lt;em&gt;Game Boy Camera&lt;/em&gt;, I did so for $20, a year after its release in the fall of 1999. I skipped the printer, which still retailed for its full price somehow. I don’t feel like I’m missing anything, especially since the Game Boy Printer is basically a repurposed receipt printer mechanism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;accessing-your-pictures&quot;&gt;Accessing Your Pictures&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;gb float left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/mgb-006/mgb-006-25.png&quot; width=&quot;480&quot; height=&quot;432&quot; alt=&quot;Game Boy Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re like me, you own a &lt;em&gt;Game Boy Camera&lt;/em&gt; with pictures that are decades old at this point. You might even have pictures that you consider valuable stuck on there. My sister had taken pictures of our family dog when he was a puppy. I wanted a way to extract them and get copies on my Mac. Having already explained how a Game Boy Printer is a poor fit for preservation, other options were needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Five or ten years ago, limited options existed but we now have a plethora of methods to extract pictures from a Game Boy, from the handmade low-run device like the &lt;a href=&quot;https://gameboyphoto.bigcartel.com/product/bitboy&quot;&gt;BitBoy&lt;/a&gt; to the exquisite FPGA high-quality device like the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.analogue.co/pocket&quot;&gt;Analogue Pocket&lt;/a&gt;. You also have the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epilogue.co/product/gb-operator&quot;&gt;Epilogue GB Operator&lt;/a&gt; a cartridge port you somehow plug into your computer to play those games, and something like the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/MattGrayYes/Game-Boy-Camera-Fast-Wifi-Adapter&quot;&gt;Game Boy Camera Fast Wifi Adapter&lt;/a&gt; a project you assemble yourself using a bunch of parts that you fit inside a 3D printed case. Basically it’s a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gbxcart.com/&quot;&gt;GBxCart RW&lt;/a&gt; coupled with a Raspberry Pi Zero. There are even more options if you want to do a bit of research. To solve the problem for me, I used something I already owned. Since I’m cheap, and didn’t want to spend money on a bespoke solution I’ll use once, I decided to use the little &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mofosyne/arduino-gameboy-printer-emulator#quick-start&quot;&gt;Arduino board I already own to transfer my pictures&lt;/a&gt;. This meant cutting up a Game Boy link cable and identifying each wire with continuity. Not the easiest thing, but it was a reasonable task for an amateur tinkerer like me. I was able to adequately mark the required wires, make new ends (always be sure to plug the ground wire in the right spot) and follow the instructions to load the software correctly and extract the data from the serial monitor. It was immediately successful, with my only issue being the extremely crappy software for the Arduino IDE. They should be ashamed of how many interface bugs they have in their software. Anyway, I encourage you to get your pictures extracted if you have any of sentimental value. That cell battery in there won’t last forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;gb&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/mgb-006/mgb-006-26.png&quot; width=&quot;480&quot; height=&quot;432&quot; alt=&quot;Game Boy Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;never-the-smallest&quot;&gt;Never the Smallest&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had read on Wikipedia that the 1999 edition of the &lt;em&gt;Guinness Book of World Records&lt;/em&gt; deemed the &lt;em&gt;Game Boy Camera&lt;/em&gt; the world’s smallest digital camera. I wanted to read this mention in Guinness directly, so I headed to the Internet Archive’s controversial book rental system to read the 1999 Guinness book. &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/guinnessbookofre00newy/page/294/mode/2up&quot;&gt;Here is the paragraph talking about the Game Boy Camera on page 294.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;art&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/mgb-006/mgb-006-27.png&quot; width=&quot;1158&quot; height=&quot;876&quot; alt=&quot;Picture&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;SMALLEST CAMERAS In 1998, Nintendo’s Game Boy, which was launched in 1989 and has sold more than 60 million units worldwide, was reinvented as a camera and printer. The digital still camera cartridge sits on top of the Game Boy (as seen at left) and can take and store up to 30 low-resolution black and white photos. The camera comes with three games that allow players to create characters using photos. The printer can then produce small prints or stickers. In 1997, the company reduced the size of the Game Boy and introduced the Game Boy Pocket, and a color version of the Game Boy is due to be launched at the end of 1998. The world’s smallest pinhole video camera is the PC-21XP, sold by Supercircuits Inc. The CCD element occupies only ¼ square inch but has a 295,000-pixel array that outputs 380 video lines. It can see in low-level lighting of 0.5 lux. The overall unit measures 115/100 × ½ inch and can run for up to five hours on one PP3 battery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see reading it, no mention is made of the Game Boy being the smallest of anything. You could perhaps read the description of the PC-21XP described as the world’s smallest pinhole video camera and think this applies to the &lt;em&gt;Game Boy Camera&lt;/em&gt;. Unfortunately, the cartridge does not use a PC-21XP as its camera element. The camera uses a &lt;a href=&quot;https://people.ece.cornell.edu/land/courses/ece4760/FinalProjects/f2012/qs44_twc55/qs44_twc55/datasheets/MITSUB_image_sensor.pdf&quot;&gt;Mitsubishi M64282FP CMOS image sensor&lt;/a&gt;. So the book actually mixes two subject matters into one paragraph, and uses the confusing title &lt;em&gt;Smallest Cameras&lt;/em&gt;. You could still read the paragraph and believe they simply did not directly write it, but the book actually names the Panasonic NV-DCF2B as the world’s smallest digital camera with a viewfinder just one page before. Reading the rest of the section on gadgets, it’s clear the paragraph is just meant to describe an interesting device. Two other devices which are not record-holders of anything are later mentioned in the same manner as the &lt;em&gt;Game Boy Camera&lt;/em&gt;: a lollipop that plays music and a 360-degree television.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be 100% sure, I contacted Guinness by email and they confirmed that the &lt;em&gt;Game Boy Camera&lt;/em&gt; was &lt;strong&gt;never assigned any record&lt;/strong&gt;. Case closed: the &lt;em&gt;Game Boy Camera&lt;/em&gt; was never the world’s smallest anything. Any mention of a Guinness record, even when properly transcribing what is written by Guinness, should be questioned. It’s always been a book of factoids and weird trivia instead of a serious reference. Reading anything related to technology feels like you’re reading a collection of statements pulled straight out from press releases. How can anyone validate the record for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/guinnessbookofre00newy/page/274/mode/2up&quot;&gt;most recyclable car&lt;/a&gt; beyond the car company’s own statement? Couple that with the broken relationship between the speed running community and Guinness, and it shows a company incapable of understanding video games. Case in point, Guinness removed Billy Mitchell’s gaming records the year after his cheating was revealed. So far so good, but they somehow &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.guinnessworldrecords.com/news/2020/6/a-statement-from-guinness-world-records-billy-mitchell-621053&quot;&gt;reinstated those same records two years later&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;after&lt;/strong&gt; he had been unequivocally proven to have lied about his achievements. He had already been &lt;a href=&quot;https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2018/04/premiere-game-scoreboard-bans-billy-mitchell-in-donkey-kong-cheating-scandal/&quot;&gt;banned from both serious &lt;em&gt;Donkey Kong&lt;/em&gt; score-keeping organizations&lt;/a&gt;. This puts Guinness under a very bad light; they have no qualms crediting records to a cheater. They also &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/0twDETh6QaI?t=3627&quot;&gt;assigned ultra-specific records to Tommy Tallarico&lt;/a&gt; in a clear example of their &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/sections/money/2017/09/20/552203402/episode-795-is-record-breaking-broken&quot;&gt;pay-for-play record scheme&lt;/a&gt;. I’m not going to mention Guinness ever again without some heavy research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wrong information about the &lt;em&gt;Game Boy Camera&lt;/em&gt; record has been on Wikipedia since it was added by an &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Game_Boy_Camera&amp;amp;diff=prev&amp;amp;oldid=219108575&quot;&gt;anonymous contributor in June 2008&lt;/a&gt;. You can now find this fake fact mentioned in tons of articles online, on Wikia, probably in a bunch of books. Look at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.digicamhistory.com/&quot;&gt;Digicam History&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.digitalkameramuseum.de/en/&quot;&gt;Digitalkameramuseum&lt;/a&gt; for example, two old websites cataloguing the pre-1999 history of digital cameras who both mention the non-existent record. I’ve emailed both to have them remove it, but I predict I will see this false information until I die.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was in high school, I would bring my Game Boy to play between classes or to show my closest friends the latest games I was playing. No one really gave a second thought that I brought my old Game Boy to school. When I ended up buying a &lt;em&gt;Game Boy Camera&lt;/em&gt;, it felt natural to show it to my friends. I was in for a rude lesson. When I brought the &lt;em&gt;Game Boy Camera&lt;/em&gt; to school, it immediately caused a ruckus. When they discovered that my Game Boy could take a picture and immediately show it on its screen, my whole class congregated around my Game Boy, rudely taking it from me. People were suddenly taking selfies, way before the concept was attached to a word, and fighting over who was going to take a picture next. It turned into a pandemonium of excited teenagers screaming at one another to have the camera. A classmate even shoved the camera down her shirt to take a picture of her cleavage. With hindsight, I saw in those five minutes the natural excitement for all the social sharing of pictures we now have in the era of the smartphone. I saw selfies before the word had left Australia, the pouty lips people make when taking those selfies, the incessant sharing of inane pictures you now see on stuff like Snapchat, and even the burgeoning concept of sexting, all with my Game Boy!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s how starved for cameras my generation was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The appeal of a cheap camera you could just play around with that you didn’t need to use carefully was hella powerful. I vividly remember not being allowed to touch the family camera; I was told I would probably break it. Everyone I knew had more or less the same experience, where a camera was an expensive tool reserved for adults. Remember, it cost money every time you pressed the shutter button. You also had to send the film to be developed, which meant that a stranger looked at every picture you took. It was common to talk about the weirdness of technicians looking at your pictures. That put social pressure on what you could shoot. I totally understand that classmate realizing she could snap her cleavage with abandon now that she knew no stranger would see the picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With class about to start, the teacher getting angsty, and me wanting to get my beloved Game Boy back, I ended up in a tussle and pushed a classmate trying to get it back. Falling down, he dropped his glasses and they broke on the ground. That’s right kids; &lt;em&gt;Game Boy Camera&lt;/em&gt; led me to violence and got me in trouble with my school principal! I was so ashamed I hid the whole thing from my parents and paid for the repair of his glasses with my own money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wouldn’t blame you if you never want to read anything from me again due to this Game Boy transgression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;gb&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/mgb-006/mgb-006-28.png&quot; width=&quot;480&quot; height=&quot;432&quot; alt=&quot;Game Boy Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

		</description>
		<link>http://localhost:4000/articles/mgb-006/</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">mgb-006</guid>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Kirby’s Dream Land</title>
		<description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;kirbys-dream-land&quot;&gt;Kirby’s Dream Land&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Japanese release in April 1992&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;North American release in August 1992&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;European release in 1992&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Published by Nintendo&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Developed by HAL Laboratory&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;boxart&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/dmg-ky/dmg-ky-1.png&quot; width=&quot;693&quot; height=&quot;800&quot; alt=&quot;Pink is in.&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pink is in.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-little-piece-of-perfection&quot;&gt;A Little Piece of Perfection&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;gb float left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/dmg-ky/dmg-ky-2.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;Game Boy Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Close your eyes for just a moment. Imagine a quiet green plain, with a comforting wind slowly swaying the grass back and forth. Near the horizon there are rose-coloured mountains. Just go along with it, rose mountains are normal. Taking in the heat of the sun’s rays (the sun has a face, once again it’s totally normal), in the swaying grass is the most serene and sweet character our imagination can muster. It’s asleep, lightly snoring as its basking in the warm glow of the beautiful day. Just like the mountains, it’s pink. It’s Kirby. A pink ball of niceness, with shoes and cute stubby arms. Its only default is its voraciousness, but it manages to make that cute too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;gb&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/dmg-ky/dmg-ky-3.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;Game Boy Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nowadays, the character’s cheery attitude has been turned into a bit of an ironic in-joke. He’s the cutest, with him being pink and always happy, but he’s also the most badass! The ultimate evil of the universe managed to destroy every single character in the introduction of &lt;em&gt;Super Smash Bros. Ultimate&lt;/em&gt;, but Kirby survived all that. &lt;em&gt;Because, you see, it’s a secret badass&lt;/em&gt;. However, the character was initially created without irony; the gumdrop aesthetic was honest. Kirby was not secretly all-powerful even though it looked harmless. There was no subversion of our expectations. In fact, the aesthetic was a core marketing element of Kirby’s first game. This evolution of Kirby’s character can perhaps be explained by the disconnect between the world of Kirby and the actions it performs. All the verbs at your disposal in &lt;em&gt;Kirby’s Dream Land&lt;/em&gt; are indistinguishable from a mature, violent side-scroller platformer like &lt;em&gt;Contra&lt;/em&gt;, if only Bill and Lance could fly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SOAR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DEVOUR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EMPOWER.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SHOOT.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ATTACK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DEFEAT.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You relentlessly move forward, mercilessly destroying your enemies by swallowing them and throwing their remains at other enemies. The visuals make it a fun jaunt and everyone is happy and cute. Isn’t that wonderful, and essential?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;setting-the-stage&quot;&gt;Setting the Stage&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;gb float right&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/dmg-ky/dmg-ky-4.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;Game Boy Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kirby is the quintessential Nintendo character, but it is not a Nintendo creation. It is not even owned by Nintendo; HAL Laboratory owns the rights. How can Kirby be a quintessential Nintendo icon if it’s owned by another company?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HAL Laboratory always had a close relationship with Nintendo, going all the way back to the Famicom. When the console was initially conceived, Nintendo had few programmers to make games for its first console with interchangeable software. The savvy people working at Nintendo turned to the people of small company HAL, who were able to help out, particularly due to one of their younger programmers, Iwata Satoru. He, along with his other colleagues, were commissioned by Nintendo to work on seminal Famicom titles like &lt;em&gt;Golf&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Balloon Fight&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Pinball&lt;/em&gt;. Their contributions stayed hidden; neither their company nor their names appeared on those Nintendo titles. When the ’90s rolled around, however, HAL had gotten in an impossible position. Their prestige 1991 Famicom game &lt;em&gt;Metal Slader Glory&lt;/em&gt; was unprofitable, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vice.com/en_us/article/ne3mjd/hal-laboratory-metal-slader-glory-nintendo-history&quot;&gt;and they were caught in a financial death spiral&lt;/a&gt;. Nintendo’s executives saw potential in HAL and bailed the company (presumably for a controlling stake), but asked that Iwata Satoru, who by this point had gotten a great reputation as a manager, &lt;a href=&quot;http://shmuplations.com/iwata/&quot;&gt;become the new company president&lt;/a&gt;. All in all, a quintessential Yamauchi Hiroshi move. Actually, this would turn out to be the most important personel move Yamauchi ever did; Iwata ended up his successor at the helm of Nintendo a decade later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;art&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/dmg-ky/dmg-ky-5.jpg&quot; width=&quot;493&quot; height=&quot;405&quot; alt=&quot;*Mingle Magnet* for Wonderswan&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mingle Magnet&lt;/em&gt; for Wonderswan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nintendo has tightened its control over HAL Laboratory ever since that fateful 1991 death spiral, with the last work of HAL not published on a Nintendo console, &lt;em&gt;Mingle Magnet&lt;/em&gt; for Wonderswan, released in 1999. They now seem to be a fully owned subsidiary, which makes them what is commonly termed a second-party developer. However, back when they made &lt;em&gt;Kirby’s Dream Land&lt;/em&gt;, they were in the process of being bailed by Nintendo. Sakurai Masahiro talked about his experience of working for a company going through bankruptcy in his &lt;a href=&quot;https://m.youtube.com/watch?v=khJa2vIW0xY&quot;&gt;Kirby’s Adventure development video on his YouTube channel&lt;/a&gt;. Kirby is the child of this marriage of convenience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;creating-a-placeholder&quot;&gt;Creating a Placeholder&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The father of Kirby, Sakurai Masahiro, was 19 when he created Kirby. He had only one other game credit under his belt, also with HAL; the interesting but obscure Game Boy shooter &lt;em&gt;Trax&lt;/em&gt;. Since Nintendo now had a hand in the management of HAL, Yamauchi Hiroshi, the ruthless Nintendo president, decided to task them with a small project to steer HAL back towards profitability. He wanted them to make a Game Boy platformer starring a new mascot. Yamauchi’s mission was accomplished with aplomb; from the moment you open your Game Boy to play &lt;em&gt;Kirby’s Dream Land&lt;/em&gt;, Kirby is a fully realized mascot in a game accessible to everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The title screen features a lineup of multiple Kirbys jumping, making faces, doing a bit of moonwalking, generally being cute as hell. You immediately get a sense of joy emanating from this little character. Aside from wondering if there are multiple Kirbys in the world (an unresolved mystery we’ll get back to shortly), you want to buy a plush Kirby just to hug it. As a first introduction its knocking it out of the park. Everything that makes Kirby lovely is there from the first moment except for its seminal copying ability which would appear in the second game. The game even manages to introduce musical themes that are still used today. As a matter of fact, the Kirby series has not only kept its songs, it kept its composer; Ishikawa Jun has always been the main composer for Kirby titles. I also want to give kudos to the sound designers for the very fun aspirating sound. Kirby sounds exactly like a vacuum, and it’s perfect. Not everything is perfect, but they clearly spent a lot of energy where it mattered for this game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-short-look-at-the-game-that-reflects-the-brevity-of-the-game&quot;&gt;A Short Look at the Game That Reflects the Brevity of the Game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some elements of the game’s design that reflect a thoughtful design process and that will enhance your experience. If you play the game, and wonder why it’s such a great little experience, then these choices explain the great fun you’re having. It’s incredible that so many magnificent design decisions were taken by a team led by such a young developer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Graphics on Game Boy require a lot of foresight and planning to work well on the original Game Boy screen because its ghosting can make complicated graphics too difficult to see. &lt;em&gt;Kirby’s Dream Land&lt;/em&gt; showcases how to create beautiful graphics that still limit the amount of ghosting, keeping the game legible in all scenarios. It amounts to using a healthy dose of whitespace with discrete elements of characters and scenery drawn with thick borders but sparse internal details. Just like Kirby, most everything in the game is a shape with very little internal detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;gb&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/dmg-ky/dmg-ky-6.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;Game Boy Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another element that really helps the fidelity of Kirby’s world is the belt scrolling. Belt scrolling describes a locked screen able to move in only one direction, with the other axis locked. The screen can move left to right but it will not move up or down and it will not reverse either. If you imagine a level as if it’s painted on an industrial belt, the crank to turn the belt can only go in one direction. Since you’re only scrolling in one plane at a time (most often in this game from left to right), the ghosting is limited to streaks going in one direction. That helps a lot since you get accustomed to the predictable unidirectional ghosting. You don’t think about it but it makes a big difference that ghosting is mostly coming from a single direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;gb&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/dmg-ky/dmg-ky-7.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;Every stage starts with a short scene of Kirby getting his comeuppance from benign situations. Here, Kirby runs after a butterfly that gets its buddies to fight back.&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;p&gt;Every stage starts with a short scene of Kirby getting his comeuppance from benign situations. Here, Kirby runs after a butterfly that gets its buddies to fight back.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;gb&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/dmg-ky/dmg-ky-8.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;Kirby tries fishing; it gets a mouthful of its own hook and falls in the water.&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kirby tries fishing; it gets a mouthful of its own hook and falls in the water.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is this saying amongst video game developers that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.designer-notes.com/?p=369&quot;&gt;if given a chance, players will optimize the fun out of a game&lt;/a&gt;. What this means is that if developers give players a cheesy strategy, players will use that advantage even if it makes the game boring to play for them. Developers have to account for this fact when designing a game, and eliminate any strategies that make playtime boring. Flying in a platformer definitely falls under that axiom; what fun is there in a game where you can fly above every obstacle and eliminate any challenge? You might have fun for a couple of minutes due to the novelty but the appeal wears off quickly. &lt;em&gt;Super Mario World&lt;/em&gt; is the golden reference when it comes to a platformer with flying elements. You can fly in the game, which could potentially ruin the fun and make the game boring. To keep the game somewhat fun even if you skip levels with the cape, you are required a lot of effort to maintain flight. It’s not a simple one button process, meaning you will always have to do something. I don’t feel it’s a perfect solution, since a repetitious task is never as fun as running through a gauntlet designed by the very best level designers in the world. &lt;em&gt;Kirby’s Dream Land&lt;/em&gt; has Kirby flying indefinitely if you inhale air. It is a dead simple one-button move, which could definitely ruin the fun. Future games in the series will slow down Kirby’s flight speed and agility, and limit your flight time. There are no such limitations here; Kirby is legitimately flying fast, by flapping its tiny little arms. However, the game is not optimizing the fun out of the platforming like &lt;em&gt;Super Mario World&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;gb float right&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/dmg-ky/dmg-ky-9.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;Game Boy Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How? The solution to the problem is actually wonderful because it uses the limitations of the Game Boy as a positive. Since the Game Boy has a limited resolution, the play area in a platformer is small. In the case of &lt;em&gt;Kirby’s Dream Land&lt;/em&gt;, the play area is around eight Kirbys tall. Compared to a game on a CRT, that’s a very small play field above your characters’ head. The smaller play field, which cannot scroll up, keeps the player involved because Kirby cannot fly very high. You just hover close to the ground, always under the threat of a jumping enemy hitting you. The game also includes many enemies who loiter around the top of the screen, giving you obstacles to avoid even when you’re in the air. So the small Game Boy screen actually makes a game more fun for once!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;unique-in-scale-and-scope&quot;&gt;Unique in Scale and Scope&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;gb float left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/dmg-ky/dmg-ky-10.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;Game Boy Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The game is simple and short, and unique in that regard. There are so few platformers like it. &lt;em&gt;Kirby’s Dream Land&lt;/em&gt; does not have a save function, but it doesn’t matter. You can easily clear the game in less than an hour. Anytime I think of a short platformer like that, all the titles that come to mind are on Game Boy, with the exception of &lt;em&gt;A Short Hike&lt;/em&gt;. I ask you, what is wrong with a game you can finish in an hour? Is there anything fundamentally wrong with an hour-long game? There isn’t, it’s simply a different artistic object. Not every platformer has to be extremely long, not every game has to stretch into infinity until you’re bored out of your head. Even the further adventures of Kirby would turn into long games immediately after this game, with &lt;em&gt;Kirby’s Adventure&lt;/em&gt; being a long-ass title requiring many hours to complete. It’s unfortunate that we were collectively offered ever longer games. We could have had tons of fun platformers like &lt;em&gt;A Short Hike&lt;/em&gt; for decades but instead everything had to be way too long all in the name of value. Ultimately, I hope we see more platformers akin to &lt;em&gt;Bowser’s Fury&lt;/em&gt; in the future; a clear concept that’s fun for around two hours. I sincerely hope that it is the future of platformers as a genre; &lt;em&gt;Mario’s Odyssey&lt;/em&gt; was way too long and meandering. I think the platforming genre would be much more vibrant and entertaining that way. Platformers could benefit from the unique experiences that a short puzzle game like &lt;em&gt;Unpacking&lt;/em&gt; provides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;gb&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/dmg-ky/dmg-ky-11.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;If you want to play the game and you want a more involved challenge, try the bonus mode. It’s properly difficult.&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you want to play the game and you want a more involved challenge, try the bonus mode. It’s properly difficult.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;marketing-meets-aesthetic&quot;&gt;Marketing Meets Aesthetic&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a link between the game’s presentation and its difficulty. Because it’s a short and easy title, it needs to tell potential buyers subconsciously. &lt;em&gt;A Short Hike&lt;/em&gt; does it by literally being called a short hike. There’s no question that this game is not meant to be difficult or long. &lt;em&gt;Kirby’s Dream Land&lt;/em&gt; features a cute character, usually a way to say that a game is for younger players. It also used the word dream in the title, which shouldn’t imply something challenging. &lt;em&gt;Kirby’s Nightmare Hellscape&lt;/em&gt; calls to mind something much different: a difficult gauntlet with demons and guns. Basically, I think of &lt;em&gt;Doom&lt;/em&gt;. I guess they ended up putting the word nightmare in the title of the remade version of &lt;em&gt;Kirby’s Adventure&lt;/em&gt; for Game Boy Advance, &lt;em&gt;Kirby: Nightmare in Dream Land&lt;/em&gt;, but by that point Kirby was a well-known and popular character. They didn’t need to signal as strongly what to expect with the marketing. &lt;em&gt;Kirby’s Dream Land&lt;/em&gt; was a smash hit in no small part due to its marketing and themes. It’s an easy platformer kids will love, but it’s so well made that everyone should play it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kirby’s Dream Land&lt;/em&gt; could only happen on Game Boy. It’s a very short game featuring very little in the way of difficultly. Because of that, it’s the first game I ever finished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was a kid, I owned two platformers at opposite ends of the Game Boy spectrum: &lt;em&gt;Donkey Kong Land&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Kirby’s Dream Land&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;/articles/dmg-yt.html&quot;&gt;I have already talked about &lt;em&gt;Donkey Kong Land&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and its atrocious choices. It’s a terrible game for the limited Game Boy screen that ignores the shortcomings of the screen. &lt;em&gt;Kirby’s Dream Land&lt;/em&gt;, released three years earlier, is in contrast a wonderful game for the unique screen of the Game Boy. It respects the limits of the portable system’s little green screen, and creates a memorable game that sets the stage for a new mascot still popular to this day. If HAL Laboratory had not respected the limits imposed on them by the Game Boy, we wouldn’t be talking about Kirby anymore, and Sakurai probably would not have become Nintendo’s biggest star developer of the 2010s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;gb&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/dmg-ky/dmg-ky-12.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;The game has a cute proper ending that rewards your efforts. Kirby turns into a hot air balloon!&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;p&gt;The game has a cute proper ending that rewards your efforts. Kirby turns into a hot air balloon!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, I totally forgot! I was supposed to get back to the mystery of the many Kirbys! When you finish the game, during the ending cinematic, Kirby can be seen dropping on a stage, with a crowd barely visible at the bottom of the screen. They’re all perfectly round shapes, only seen in shadows, which leads me to believe that Kirby was envisionned as the member of a whole species of Kirbys.&lt;/p&gt;

		</description>
		<link>http://localhost:4000/articles/dmg-ky/</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">dmg-ky</guid>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Mole Mania</title>
		<description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;mole-mania&quot;&gt;Mole Mania&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Japanese release in July 1996&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;North American release in February 1997&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;European release in 1997&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Published by Nintendo&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Developed by Nintendo EAD &amp;amp; Pax Softnica&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;boxart&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/dmg-amoe/dmg-amoe-1.jpg&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;639&quot; alt=&quot;It’s a mole with glasses!&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;p&gt;It’s a mole with glasses!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;buried-treasure&quot;&gt;Buried Treasure&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;gb float left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/dmg-amoe/dmg-amoe-2.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;Game Boy Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yokoi Gunpei, the father of the Game Boy, was in a weird spot. He was the company’s oldest team leader at Nintendo but his reputation was shot. Inside the company, he was seen as having lost his way, having spent too much of the company’s time and effort on a failed project with no appeal, the Virtual Boy. It was the epitome of his creed of using old technology in surprising ways (usually translated as &lt;em&gt;Lateral Thinking with Withered Technology&lt;/em&gt;) but it lacked the fun factor that made Nintendo into a household name, resulting in a very public failure for the company. Yokoi had planned on leaving Nintendo right after the release of the Virtual Boy. His interest in seeing the new console to release was the only thing keeping him at Nintendo. With that project a burning red failure, Yokoi stayed; he wanted to leave on a positive note, not in disgrace. To that end, he looked at the original Game Boy. It ran laps around the competition of portable consoles but all the media outlets were wondering why there was no new hardware. The answer was pure Nintendo: they were intent on maintaining the same principle that made the Game Boy a success of not compromising on battery life. Since there was no new CPU or screen tech that would provide a better experience while maintaining a reasonable battery life, Yokoi Gunpei tasked himself and his team with making a better version of the already existing Game Boy. This project would ultimately lead to the Game Boy Pocket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Nintendo kept the same muted, simple strategy for its portable behemoth, Game Boy games were getting rarer. To keep shelves stocked with good games, Nintendo started their Players’ Choice program. &lt;a href=&quot;/articles/dmg-zl/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Legend of Zelda: Link’s Awakening&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Star Wars&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/articles/dmg-bb/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Bugs Bunny Crazy Castle&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/articles/dmg-rw/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mega Man: Dr. Wily’s Revenge&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; are just some examples of games republished by Nintendo under their Players’ Choice banner. Clearly, the company was trying to put older titles of better quality on store shelves to maintain interest for the Game Boy and its new upgrade the Game Boy Pocket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While in Japan &lt;em&gt;Pokémon&lt;/em&gt; was out since February of ’96, the global future was uncertain. It was a truly gangbuster success locally, that had given a second wind to the Game Boy, but could this success be replicated outside Japan? Could Game Freak, an unproven group of young inexperienced people, provide more Pokémon games to solidify the mania? How long would people buy Game Boy systems to play &lt;em&gt;Pokémon&lt;/em&gt;? Nothing was certain. Out of this weird middle age for the Game Boy, Game Boy Pocket was born. With that new console revision came one marquee title to coincide with the release, the fourth and final Nintendo EAD developed game for Game Boy: &lt;em&gt;Mole Mania&lt;/em&gt;. A puzzle game pitting you as a mole that pushes and throws things while digging holes, the best way to describe it would be to compare it to the action puzzle games of the ’80s like &lt;em&gt;Sokoban&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Lode Runner&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I cannot say it loud enough: play this game! &lt;em&gt;Mole Mania&lt;/em&gt; is very good. It’s a Miyamoto Shigeru masterpiece done during his golden age, when his output was arguably at his summit. He was supervising classics like &lt;em&gt;Yoshi’s Island&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Super Mario 64&lt;/em&gt;, and here comes this game done in a genre that he had abandoned, and he brings all the lessons he learned since he last made an action puzzle game. It’s a true bona fide classic, and it’s absolutely &lt;strong&gt;forgotten&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-hole-game&quot;&gt;A Hole Game&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since this is a top-of-the-line Nintendo game, all the bad things about action puzzle games are smoothed out. There are so many pitfalls the game could have fallen into, but you can see they play-tested the hell out of the game to make it fun. Unlike &lt;em&gt;Lode Runner&lt;/em&gt;, the enemies of the game stick to predictable patterns. They never run toward you, Terminator-style, making you run for your life every instant. Instead, &lt;strong&gt;you&lt;/strong&gt; get in &lt;strong&gt;their&lt;/strong&gt; way, because they follow a pattern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s always a short way to reset a puzzle. Like &lt;em&gt;Sokoban&lt;/em&gt;, you can get objects stuck, but there’s a very simple way to reset a puzzle. You just leave the screen and come back. A menu option also exists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every puzzle has the same solution: push the black ball against the rock blocking the path to the next screen. So you can fixate on getting that ball where it needs to go. There are multiple objects you can push, but they always gravitate around getting out of the black ball’s way. However, the game often gives you more objects than you need. A pipe elbow will be pointless and irrelevant to the solution of the puzzle. Thus, puzzles are not always &lt;em&gt;clean&lt;/em&gt;, meaning that you have more than what you need to finish the puzzle. On top of that, there are sometimes multiple methods to clear an exit. This is particularly apparent in level 4, where you have in quick succession multiple types of puzzles. So, when reaching a new screen, you immediately need to figure out whether there are objects that are useless to complete the level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game’s core gameplay is a throwback to games like &lt;em&gt;Devil’s World&lt;/em&gt; and other early Famicom titles. Like those games, it’s a single-screen affair, very interested in providing time-sensitive puzzles and filled with unbeatable enemies that need to be avoided. It’s a game that reflects back on the era when everybody was improving on the &lt;em&gt;Pac-Man&lt;/em&gt; formula. &lt;em&gt;Mole Mania&lt;/em&gt; should have happened in the ’80s when you look at its lineage and genre but everything else about the game is very 1996. The presentation is flawless, the game is littered with valuable secrets. It has boss battles and bonus stages, and the ability to be played somewhat non-sequentially, so you can come back later to a puzzle that stumps you. All elements that were common by 1996.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It feels like Miyamoto was thinking of an interesting project to do and saying &lt;em&gt;I know how to do this effortlessly&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;he actually does&lt;/strong&gt;. The presentation is as good as any mid 90s era SNES or N64 game with its distinct worlds, story told through the environment and anime-inspired premise. &lt;em&gt;Mole Mania&lt;/em&gt; is what happens when a developer goes back to older concepts and looks at those old tropes with their improved experience. Miyamoto knew how to push the contractors at Pax Softnica, with which he had already released two other Game Boy games, to refine the concepts until they were flawless, he knew how to remove anything superfluous so the game was easy to understand, and he knew how to build on his simple idea until it becomes delightfully hard while keeping its original core concept. Miyamoto in 1984, when he originally made games that look like &lt;em&gt;Mole Mania&lt;/em&gt; was not &lt;strong&gt;that&lt;/strong&gt; good. It might be my bias but I think &lt;em&gt;Mole Mania&lt;/em&gt; is Miyamoto at his best. It was made in the same era as &lt;em&gt;Super Mario 64&lt;/em&gt;, Nintendo EAD’s masterpiece. I can imagine a stressed out Miyamoto coming out of a difficult &lt;em&gt;Super Mario 64&lt;/em&gt; design meeting and going to speak to the people making &lt;em&gt;Mole Mania&lt;/em&gt; afterwards to relax with something relatively simple. Something where he already knew how to solve the problems, where he wasn’t confronted with 3D problems he had no idea existed and still had to figure out. Imagine how much easier it is to work on &lt;em&gt;Mole Mania&lt;/em&gt; when you spent the whole day trying to figure out how to control the camera in &lt;em&gt;Super Mario 64&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The original Game Boy is at its best with this game; to me &lt;em&gt;Mole Mania&lt;/em&gt; is a gift from above. I’ve adored Miyamoto’s trifecta of the late ’90s: &lt;em&gt;Yoshi’s Island&lt;/em&gt;, which he believed to be his last 2D platformer, &lt;em&gt;Super Mario 64&lt;/em&gt;, his success at inventing how to jump and explore a 3D world, and &lt;em&gt;The Legend of Zelda: Ocarina of Time&lt;/em&gt;, the refinement of everything learned making those two other games. I thought I had played all his games made during that era, but here we have a fourth, lesser work, done with the same talent by the same man and I had never played it. I can’t bring myself to finish &lt;em&gt;Mole Mania&lt;/em&gt; since when I’m done I won’t have any games from golden age Miyamoto.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a last aside, &lt;em&gt;Mole Mania&lt;/em&gt; gives a great example against the concept of console generations to classify video games. Go read about video game history on Wikipedia for example, or pick up any lesser book, and you’ll be very quickly presented with this idea of console generations defining the whole industry. It’s everywhere, to the point where developers themselves constantly discuss their work in the context of generations. While generations can make some sense if only TV consoles existed, portable systems exist and are just as important. A game like &lt;em&gt;Mole Mania&lt;/em&gt;, and any Game Boy game released in 1996, is considered in the same goddamn generation as the Famicom released in 1983. &lt;em&gt;Mole Mania&lt;/em&gt; was developed by Miyamoto concurrently with &lt;em&gt;Super Mario 64&lt;/em&gt;. Both titles are brethrens, directed by the same man at the same time. So that’s why I’m against the concept of generations, which is player-centric, while video games are made by artists, and artistic considerations and mindsets are more important than marketing categorization. &lt;em&gt;Mole Mania&lt;/em&gt; embodies that idea perfectly.&lt;/p&gt;

		</description>
		<link>http://localhost:4000/articles/dmg-amoe/</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">dmg-amoe</guid>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Pokémon: Red, Green &amp; Blue</title>
		<description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;pokémon-red-green--blue&quot;&gt;Pokémon: Red, Green &amp;amp; Blue&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Japanese release in February 1996 of Red &amp;amp; Green and October 1996 of Blue (exclusive to CoroCoro Comic)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;North American release in September 1998 based on Japanese Blue&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;European release in October 1999&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Published by Nintendo&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Developed by Game Freak&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;boxart&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/dmg-apee/dmg-apee-1.jpg&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;800&quot; alt=&quot;Green Version?&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;p&gt;Green Version?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-game-boy-resurrection&quot;&gt;A Game Boy Resurrection&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;gb float left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/dmg-apee/dmg-apee-2.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;Game Boy Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before it became a perennial staple of popular culture with its card games and anime series and yearly releases, &lt;em&gt;Pokémon&lt;/em&gt; was a world filled with mysteries. Friends would trade Pokémon monsters using the Link Cable, but they would also trade legends, tall tales of dubious veracity, secret incantations of duplications and methods to find strange and forbidden monsters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why, dear reader, I invite you to follow me starting on Route 1 throughout Kanto as I unveil the answer to the following mysteries:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What Secret Game Probably Inspired Pokémon’s Creator?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What Did Game Freak Publish Before Making Video Games?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Which Surprising Pokémon Was Born First?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What Horrible NES Game Funded the Development of Pokémon?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Who Really Owns the Pokémon Franchise?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Why Does the Game Have a Green Version in Japan?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Why Did It Take Two Years for the Game to Be Localized and Released in North America?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How Did Pokémon Teach Me About the Idiosyncratic Québec Media Landscape?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Are There More Than 150 Pokémon?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is the Game Any Good?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, maybe that mystery about the amount of Pokémon is a bit dated, considering there are now [he looks at Bulbapedia] 901 Pokémon, and that’s without counting all those variants and gigantic versions of all the old ones. I even heard there are some Pokémon amongst the newer ones that aren’t well designed! Gasp!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s forget all about those newer creations, and go back to a time when everybody was wondering if there would ever be another game and Pikablu had not yet captured our imaginations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-secret-game-probably-inspired-pokémons-creator&quot;&gt;What secret game probably inspired Pokémon’s creator?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;art float right&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/dmg-apee/dmg-apee-3.png&quot; width=&quot;1000&quot; height=&quot;1272&quot; alt=&quot;Picture&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, though, let’s go even further back, to 1989, to reveal the answer to our first mystery. Tajiri Satoshi, &lt;em&gt;Pokémon&lt;/em&gt;’s creator, had a very fruitful first encounter with the Game Boy. While people were immediately drawn to the screen of the portable device, Tajiri was inspired by a humbler element of the console; its Link Cable. He imagined little insects travelling along the wire, going from one Game Boy to the other. From this simple idea, &lt;em&gt;Pokémon&lt;/em&gt; was born. At least that’s the myth, told time and time again by Satoshi to explain the genesis of his concept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m a bit skeptical of this perfect story, absent of any influence from other video games. He knew video games well, and I refuse to believe Satoshi wasn’t influenced by &lt;em&gt;Makai Toushi SaGa&lt;/em&gt;. Known in the West as &lt;em&gt;The Final Fantasy Legend&lt;/em&gt;, it’s the first role-playing game for the system, coming in a mere six months after the system’s initial release. It showed that the Game Boy was a perfect system for RPGs. I covered it previously, and I marvelled at how it attempted so much, so early in the system’s life. The game features monsters in your party, that can evolve (and devolve) based on eating the meat of your defeated enemies. I’m inclined to believe that Satoshi played &lt;em&gt;Makai Toushi SaGa&lt;/em&gt; and got some inspiration from the game. Perhaps he even dreamed not of insects travelling along the wire, but of the monsters in &lt;em&gt;Makai Toushi SaGa&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t want to diminish the accomplishments, especially since the monster trading is a novel idea worth all the praise it has gotten, but there is this tendency with developers, and Japanese developers in particular, to shy away from mentioning inspirations from other video games. All we can do is presume, which is what I’m doing here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-did-game-freak-publish-before-making-video-games&quot;&gt;What Did Game Freak Publish Before Making Video Games?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Satoshi was a publisher of a fanzine focusing on arcade titles, which he worked on alongside Sugimori Ken, the artist drawing the fanzine’s art. Ken would later become the main artist for the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;art&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/dmg-apee/dmg-apee-4.jpg&quot; width=&quot;768&quot; height=&quot;1024&quot; alt=&quot;Picture&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saw some original copies of their fanzine in a museum exhibit, and they were underwhelming. There’s no magical quality to them; they were low quality Japanese fanzines, made with a lot of love but still simply fanzines. Those little staples books are relevant because they birthed Game Freak and put Satoshi and Ken together, allowing them to later pivot to video game development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;which-surprising-pokémon-was-born-first&quot;&gt;Which Surprising Pokémon Was Born First?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bulbapedia.bulbagarden.net/wiki/Capsule_Monsters&quot;&gt;The original concept for Capsule Monsters&lt;/a&gt;, which would become &lt;em&gt;Pocket Monsters&lt;/em&gt; before release, used generic creatures that looked like dragons and dinosaurs. Amongst those dinosaur-looking creatures, one has been identified as the first Pokémon, the first creature that was imagined during this early concept and survived all the way to the release of the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;art&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/dmg-apee/dmg-apee-5.jpg&quot; width=&quot;1000&quot; height=&quot;1113&quot; alt=&quot;Hey look who’s in the back of this very early sketch.&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hey look who’s in the back of this very early sketch.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rhydon was the oldest design to end up in the final game. He is a very generic-looking dinosaur with a rhinoceros horn, so it makes a ton of sense that he is the oldest Pokémon, coming from the era where all the creatures were inspired by dinosaurs. More creative concepts like Electabuzz would come later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-horrible-nes-game-funded-the-development-of-pokémon&quot;&gt;What Horrible NES Game Funded the Development of Pokémon?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once again I have to make a personal connection before I answer the question because I’m a raging narcissist. When the Super Nintendo came out, I didn’t have one. I had gotten a second-hand NES earlier in the year, so, of course, my mother was not about to start upgrading her six-year-old son with the latest and greatest. Since I was smitten with Yoshi and dreamed of nothing but riding him in &lt;em&gt;Super Mario World&lt;/em&gt;, I asked my mom to buy me &lt;em&gt;Yoshi&lt;/em&gt; for NES as a birthday gift, and when I started playing it this is what I saw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;pixel&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/dmg-apee/dmg-apee-6.png&quot; width=&quot;292&quot; height=&quot;240&quot; alt=&quot;What a giant piece of shit.&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;p&gt;What a giant piece of shit.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a shitty puzzle game. To rub even more salt in the wound, there’s a better Yoshi puzzle game, &lt;em&gt;Yoshi’s Cookie&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Yoshi&lt;/em&gt; is not even half as good as &lt;em&gt;Yoshi’s Cookie&lt;/em&gt;. It’s just terribly uninspired and boring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what’s the Pokémon connection? Game Freak was cash poor during the early ’90s, and Nintendo bailed them out because they believed in their Pocket Monsters concept. I think part of the help they got from Nintendo was to be assigned to develop &lt;em&gt;Yoshi&lt;/em&gt;. This allowed them to make enough money on a surefire hit based on a hot new character, and to learn the complicated details of video game development. They could keep going and maintain the development of &lt;em&gt;Pokémon&lt;/em&gt;, using the money they made from &lt;em&gt;Yoshi&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I can sleep at night, knowing that I directly financed the development of Pokémon all the way back in 1992. Well, I guess my mom financed the development of &lt;em&gt;Pokémon&lt;/em&gt;. Be sure to thank my mom if you see her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;who-really-owns-the-pokémon-franchise&quot;&gt;Who Really Owns the Pokémon Franchise?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When &lt;em&gt;Pokémon Go&lt;/em&gt; was initially released on iOS and became &lt;strong&gt;the&lt;/strong&gt; global phenomenon in the summer of 2016, Nintendo’s stock in the Tokyo stock Exchange suddenly doubled. Nintendo, unfortunately, could not enjoy this sudden excitement for their stock. Because they knew that investors would cool when they learned that Nintendo is not the master of the Pokémon franchise. &lt;a href=&quot;https://time.com/4421450/pokemon-go-nintendo-shares-tokyo/&quot;&gt;They clarified their complicated relationship with Pokémon Go, and the stock went back down&lt;/a&gt;. It’s obvious they were scared the stock would fall &lt;strong&gt;harder&lt;/strong&gt; once the game was monetized and Nintendo would make no money from the game. You see, Nintendo didn’t make &lt;em&gt;Pokémon Go&lt;/em&gt;, and they don’t even wholly own the Pokémon franchise. In fact, they do not receive direct revenue from &lt;em&gt;Pokémon&lt;/em&gt;. What? Nintendo doesn’t outright own Pokémon? Then who does? Three companies do, with a fourth special case, and let’s go through each one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;game-freak&quot;&gt;Game Freak&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The OG gang, the company created by Tajiri Satoshi, Masuda Jun’ichi and Sugimori Ken to publish their fanzine that later transitioned to video game development. It is at this company that Tajiri created the whole Pokémon concept and it is still to this day the birthplace of any new concept or monster. No other developer or licensee can willy-nilly create a new Pokémon called Pikatwo; Game Freak is the sole place where new Pokémon are birthed. They have stayed a small developer, even though they’re the idea factory of the largest media franchise in the world. The small size is seemingly to foster creativity and maintain a high level of control. Whenever anybody complains that the graphics in a Pokémon game are terrible, their minuscule size is the reason. They simply do not have the manpower to rival the bigger studios inside Nintendo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like I just mentioned, they’re the company responsible for the development of Pokémon games, but only what is usually called the core games; think &lt;em&gt;Pokémon Sun&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Pokémon Legends: Arceus&lt;/em&gt;. Altough that distinction is getting muddled, with the latest remakes, &lt;em&gt;Brilliant Diamond&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Shining Pearl&lt;/em&gt; being developed by ILCA, a relatively obscure Japanese developer. Quick aside, they obviously delegated those two remakes to ILCA to work as much as possible on &lt;em&gt;Pokémon Legends: Arceus&lt;/em&gt;, a top to bottom reinvention of the game concept. With, once again, terrible graphics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;nintendo&quot;&gt;Nintendo&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Between the birth of the idea from the mind of Tajiri Satoshi and the release of the first game in 1996, Game Freak presented the project to Nintendo, and the company became its publisher. Nintendo also acquired a stake in the franchise itself. This is particular since a publisher does not necessarily own the intellectual property of the game it publishes: you can look at &lt;em&gt;Banjo-Kazooie&lt;/em&gt; for example, initially published by Nintendo in the ’90s but now available on Microsoft consoles. This could happen because the company that made the game, Rare, did not sell the ownership of the copyright to Nintendo even though Nintendo owned a controlling stake in Rare; they instead collaborated on the development and distribution. If I had to hazard a guess as to why Nintendo bought a stake in the Pokémon franchise itself, I’d say it’s because Game Freak needed the money to finish the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In direct terms, Nintendo shares the Pokémon copyright with the other three companies holding it. It shares the trademark in Japan with those three companies, and is the sole owner of the trademark in the rest of the world. Don’t forget to look up the difference between a copyright and a trademark, kids. This share of the franchise means Nintendo considers &lt;em&gt;Pokémon&lt;/em&gt; its own: Pikachu and the rest were in &lt;em&gt;Super Smash Bros.&lt;/em&gt; from the first game’s release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To most people, everything related to Pokémon is made by Nintendo, when the truth is far more complicated. Nintendo’s not even the sole publisher of the Pokémon games on Nintendo’s own consoles. They share that role with the Pokémon Company that they also happen to co-own with the other companies with which it shares the Pokémon copyright. I told you it was complicated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;creatures-inc&quot;&gt;Creatures Inc.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who is Creatures Inc. exactly? It makes a ton of sense that Game Freak and Nintendo share the franchise, but why is there a third company in the mix? According to Masuda Junichi, a co-founder of Game Freak and the current creative overseer for the games, they were the producers of the first game. This is strange since the producer of a game is usually a person working for the company making the game, not an outside company. Thinking about the situation, I don’t think they’ll ever admit it, but I think Creatures Inc. was brought in to help Tajiri finish the game. He couldn’t do it alone since he had never produced a game before: he was a fanzine writer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The history of Creatures Inc. also seems to confirm my thinking. Creatures Inc. is made-up of former employees of Ape Inc., who supported a visionary artist with no video game experience to produce a very personal RPG based on a fairy-tale version of our modern world. I’m, of course, not talking of &lt;em&gt;Pokémon&lt;/em&gt; but of Itoi Shigesato and his game &lt;em&gt;Mother&lt;/em&gt;, which we know in the West as &lt;em&gt;Earthbound Beginnings&lt;/em&gt;. It turns out the employees of Creatures Inc. helped with the same job twice!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since they helped finish the first Pokémon game, their contract clearly gave them partial ownership of the franchise, and they went on to create the Pokémon trading card game (it wasn’t made by Wizards of the Coast, who simply localized it) and other elements of the franchise. Once again, if I had to guess as to why Creatures own a part of the franchise, it’s because Game Freak couldn’t pay them to help them, so they paid them with a franchise stake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-pokémon-company&quot;&gt;The Pokémon Company&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Created by all three above companies to initially manage the &lt;em&gt;Pokémon Center&lt;/em&gt; stores popping up in Japan in the early ’90s as The Pokémon Center Company, it quickly became the company managing the licensing of Pokémon. So if a toiletry company wants to put Pikachu on a towel, they call The Pokémon Company, not Nintendo. The question arises, though: why not let Nintendo manage the licensing?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These days, Nintendo is good at licensing its characters for interesting products. I’m particularly impressed by the Mario Lego sets, with its special Mario Lego character with screens for eyes, a small speaker and an NFC reader allowing him to emote and react to specially tagged bricks. Or &lt;em&gt;Mario Kart Live&lt;/em&gt;, the toy that allows you to kart race in your own home. In the mid ’90s, however, Nintendo was only able to give adequate focus to the Japanese market. Licensed Nintendo products overseas like toys, cereals, books, or content like TV shows and movies, were all terrible. &lt;a href=&quot;https://gamehistory.org/watch-nintendo-power-reunion/&quot;&gt;In a recent reunion organized by the VGHF, Gail Tilden, first editor-in-chief of Nintendo Power Magazine&lt;/a&gt;, mentioned that licensing at Nintendo throughout the ’90s was barebones, and that the magazine had to do any sort of marketing material on its own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I don’t believe Nintendo was prepared to deal with Pokémon: they never managed to license anything worthwhile related to &lt;em&gt;The Legend of Zelda&lt;/em&gt;, for example. They were a toy maker, not a licensing manager. So a fourth company was emboldened to manage everything related to licensed Pokémon products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Pokémon Company now even co-publishes the games on Nintendo consoles, and has become the sort of brand manager for Pokémon in its entirety, managing tournaments, products and announcements related to the franchise. So they have never stopped growing their importance as time went on. If one company is responsible for the management and mistakes made with the franchise now, it’s them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-does-the-game-have-a-green-version-in-japan&quot;&gt;Why Does the Game Have a Green Version in Japan?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon its initial release in Japan, the two versions of the game were the red and green versions. Most people are aware of this regional difference in versions, since the remakes on Game Boy Advance feature those original colours, but I still feel compelled to explain it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Pokémon was first released, one of its fascinating creations was the concept of the dual versions. To foster the trading of Pokémon between players, the game came in two flavours, green and red, with a specific subset of Pokémon unique to each game. This meant that to complete your Pokédex (that you had owned one copy of every creature) you had to trade with someone else. Someone with a different version. There isn’t an overwhelming list of Pokémon unique to each version, just a handful, but it taught everyone that Pokémon is about trading with other players.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the Japanese in early 1996 were going crazy over those two initial versions, &lt;em&gt;Pocket Monsters: Red&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Pocket Monsters: Green&lt;/em&gt;, players also discovered the game had some rough edges. The graphics were clunky, the monsters didn’t look exactly the same as in the manual illustrations, and the game had some unfortunate bugs. A version that fixed some of the bugs and featured updated graphics was released later in 1996. This was called &lt;em&gt;Pocket Monsters: Blue&lt;/em&gt;. All the later localization work was based on this improved game, so no one outside Japan ever saw the original graphics. They kept the original monster distribution from Japanese Red for international Red, and transposed the Green distribution into the international Blue version. At this point, why not go all the way and localize Green instead? I guess Blastoise has cannons, that’s too cool to pass up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll talk about Yellow some other time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-did-it-take-two-years-for-the-game-to-be-localized-and-released-in-north-america&quot;&gt;Why Did It Take Two Years for the Game to Be Localized and Released in North America?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one is easy to answer: &lt;em&gt;Dragon Quest&lt;/em&gt;. Back in the days of the Famicom, &lt;em&gt;Dragon Quest&lt;/em&gt; seduced the Japanese with its quirky reinvention of the role-playing game. By &lt;em&gt;Dragon Quest III&lt;/em&gt;, the series was a societal phenomenon. Enix famously moved releases to Saturdays, to alleviate public concerns from some Diet legislators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pocket Monsters&lt;/em&gt; was obviously going in the same direction in Japan. Everybody and their mother knew about the game, and anything related to the franchise was a guaranteed revenue windfall. But there was one major flaw with &lt;em&gt;Dragon Quest&lt;/em&gt;: no one cared about it outside of Japan. It had its fans, but Nintendo was directly stung by its poor North American reception. They published the localization in North America and had such a sale dud that they had to give copies with Nintendo Power subscriptions to get rid of their unsold copies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This failure led to years of statements by employees of Nintendo that non-Japanese players didn’t like RPGs. They weren’t wrong; RPGs sold far less in North America than in Japan, but it was a chicken or the egg situation. RPGs had a ton of text to localize, which meant a protracted localization process, and used far more memory, which all meant a more expensive product. For these reasons, few Japanese RPGs were localized and brought West, meaning it was much harder to build an audience for the few games that did see a release. When Nintendo tried their hands at bringing RPGs to North America, they always had disappointing results. &lt;em&gt;Earthbound&lt;/em&gt; left a particularly sour taste to everyone involved at Nintendo of America, &lt;a href=&quot;https://gamehistory.org/ep-74-pokemons-translator-nob-ogasawara/&quot;&gt;according to &lt;em&gt;Pokémon&lt;/em&gt; translator Nob Ogasawara&lt;/a&gt;. It was very difficult to translate, with &lt;em&gt;Mother&lt;/em&gt; creator Itoi Shigesato getting directly involved, and sold very poorly, killing any hope to reverse the trend of underperforming RPGs with &lt;em&gt;Earthbound&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This illustrates how careful everyone at Nintendo was regarding &lt;em&gt;Pocket Monsters&lt;/em&gt;. It was yet another reinvention of the role-playing game, and the same lack of interest for the genre could hurt them once again, just like &lt;em&gt;Dragon Quest&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Mother&lt;/em&gt;/&lt;em&gt;Earthbound&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They had to try releasing it outside Japan, it would be ridiculous not to, but they wanted to take their time to get it right. They considered redesigning the creatures, but ultimately abandoned the idea. Time was ticking, and on top of that the industry had started to change since the release of &lt;em&gt;Dragon Warrior&lt;/em&gt;. We were now under the auspices of an entertainment model. In effect, the marketing challenge for game publishers had shifted from getting a consumer to buy your game to getting a retailer to stock your game in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Starting around 1994, the software industry transitioned to what Nina Schulyer called the “entertainment model” of marketing. If retail shelf space was harder to come by and lasted for a shorter time, the idea was to put more resources into generating hype in advance, raising awareness for the title before it was even released, the same way Hollywood studios promoted movies. […] It’s no coincidence that right around this time also marked the beginning of Electronic Entertainment Expo (E3), a massive game industry marketing event that was originally intended as a way to advertise directly to retailers. &lt;a href=&quot;https://obscuritory.com/essay/incredible-boxes-of-hock-wah-yeo/&quot;&gt;Source.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nintendo could not put a game on the shelves and spend months hyping it like they did in 1989 with &lt;em&gt;Dragon Warrior&lt;/em&gt;; retailers did not have the patience for that. Considering the original &lt;em&gt;Pocket Monsters&lt;/em&gt; in Japan became a phenomenon through word of mouth and needed months to reach its sale potential, it benefitted greatly from the old model where the game sat on shelves waiting for consumers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So Nintendo, Game Freak and Creatures wisely prepared something special for the release of Pokémon. Nintendo internally translated most of the core concepts of the game, and would then use those translated Pokémon names and concepts for the anime localization. Those two products, game and anime, would both release together in the fall of 1998. A one-two punch of Pokémon content, which would hopefully entice american children. For good measure, the surprisingly successful Trading Card Game would follow the next spring, distributed by Wizards of the Coast, the people behind &lt;em&gt;Magic: The Gathering&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It took them a while to arrive at this plan, and required a lot of effort to implement. History vindicated their patience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-did-pokémon-teach-me-about-the-idiosyncratic-québec-media-landscape&quot;&gt;How Did Pokémon Teach Me About the Idiosyncratic Québec Media Landscape?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was 10 in 1996 when &lt;em&gt;Pocket Monsters&lt;/em&gt; was released in Japan. I was still playing with my Game Boy, even though it felt like the rest of the world had moved on. Games were still available, but the recent releases left me unimpressed. I focused my attention on playing older releases whenever I could.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I started hearing a rumour, from magazines and video game TV shows, about this new Game Boy title made by Nintendo. A game were you explored a world full of monsters. You captured and befriended those monsters to fight other trainers, never fighting them yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I obviously knew that Nintendo and all my favourite video games were made in Japan but here was rare news about an exciting &lt;strong&gt;Game Boy&lt;/strong&gt; title. The really crazy part, though, was that the game was a massive cultural phenomenon in Japan. The news and articles were saying that everyone was playing it. What? Everybody was playing a Game Boy game in 1996? It was unbelievable to my young brain. I thought I was the only person still playing the Game Boy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have to do a bit of mental work here, dear reader, to forget the existence of Pokémon. It’s not an easy thing to do. Pokémon is according to most metrics the most profitable media franchise &lt;strong&gt;ever&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You think the Marvel Cinematic Universe is bigger? Nope. They don’t have much reach outside the movies and TV shows themselves, so it’s not enough revenue to compete.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Star Wars, with its forty years of associated toy sales? It’s not enough of a success outside North America, particularly in Asia, to compete. Star Wars was bigger than Pokémon in the US, but never worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Star Trek? The Pokémon trading card game alone is bigger than all of Star Trek at an estimated ten billion dollars in card revenue since its release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pokémon is simply the biggest media franchise ever, and it’s as relevant now all around the globe in 2022 as it has ever been. But there was a time before Pokémon was a global phenomenon. For a time, it was strictly a Japanese affair. The rest of the world could only stay outside, trying to look inside. And we’re not talking months here. Pokémon remained a Japanese phenomenon for two years. The rest of the world could only get an outside glimpse at the craze for a very long time. The trading card game, a Nintendo 64 game that allowed you to fight using your Pokémon on your Game Boy cartridge, a manga, the anime, even the first movie were all released before Pokémon left Japan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pokémon&lt;/em&gt; was finally released in North America in the Fall of 1998, and it promptly flew over my head. I didn’t notice it was released. I was unaware that the Japanese phenomenon had finally crossed the Pacific. I didn’t even know they had decided on &lt;em&gt;Pokémon&lt;/em&gt; as its English name. How could that be? &lt;em&gt;Pokémon&lt;/em&gt; was released in North America along with the anime. It was everywhere. How could I completely miss this release? Before I answer that question, let’s move forward in time to early 1999, when I saw the best video game publicity ever made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;art&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/dmg-apee/dmg-apee-7.png&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;480&quot; alt=&quot;Strictly based on this ad’s sense of humour, I decided to buy the game.&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;p&gt;Strictly based on this ad’s sense of humour, I decided to buy the game.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Super Smash Bros.&lt;/em&gt; came out in April of 1999 and I bought it as soon as possible with my hard-earned paperboy money. &lt;em&gt;Super Smash Bros.&lt;/em&gt; obviously features Pikachu, and even Jigglypuff, as playable characters. There’s a stage from the franchise as well, and you can even use Pokéballs. I immediately got very curious once I started playing. There’s a yellow electric rat constantly screaming his own name that’s given as much reverence as gaming Jesus, our lord and stomper, Mario. What was the deal with that? So I remembered all those rumblings about the pocket monster game, and figured that the game must be this Pokémon thing I was seeing in Smash. When I looked at the Works section in Pikachu’s character sheet, his single released game was there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;pixel&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/dmg-apee/dmg-apee-8.png&quot; width=&quot;645&quot; height=&quot;480&quot; alt=&quot;That’s how old I am kids. I learned that Pokémon was released from the *Super Smash Bros.* character biographies.&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;p&gt;That’s how old I am kids. I learned that Pokémon was released from the &lt;em&gt;Super Smash Bros.&lt;/em&gt; character biographies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I finally ended up seeing both the Red and Blue games at my local Zellers. How could I miss the media onslaught of &lt;em&gt;Pokémon&lt;/em&gt; and being surprised at the presence of Pikachu in &lt;em&gt;Super Smash Bros.&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because I’m Québécois. In Québec, the language barrier meant we got some types of media later than the United States and Canada. Big popular movies came out dubbed in French at basically the same time, but books and especially TV shows were on a different timeframe as the rest of North America. An American TV show had to become popular enough to warrant shopping it around internationally, then it has to be licensed and dubbed by a Québec TV network and only then can it be put on their schedule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t go thinking that Québec always uses dubs made in France. A lot of French dubs for movies and TV shows are meant to be used internationally; they’ll use language understandable across &lt;em&gt;la francophonie&lt;/em&gt;, and use a toned down Parisian accent informally called international French. These dubs are common in Québec for movies and TV shows, but not all dubbing follows these constraints. Comedic and lighthearted content, like a Japanese anime about a boy capturing local wildlife in red balls, is better served by a local dub, since it can more accurately reflect the local inflection and sense of humour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doing a cursory investigation tells me that Québec would usually get popular American TV shows a year later than in the US during the ’80s and ’90s, whether a French or Québec dub was used. That is if the show came to Québec at all. Some TV shows were never broadcast in Québec, and others, like American single-camera sitcoms were never popular in Québec. They’re cheap to make, so Québec produced its own sitcoms that were more popular than the American ones. Shows like &lt;em&gt;Friends&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Seinfeld&lt;/em&gt; were not particularly popular, in large part due to their use of a French from France dub.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the overwhelming majority of video games were not translated at the time (publishers were finally required by law to offer French versions of their games in 2007) and would come out at the same time in both markets. This led to interesting situations in Québec. For example, the Capcom game of &lt;em&gt;Chip ’n Dale: Rescue Rangers&lt;/em&gt; for NES was available &lt;strong&gt;before&lt;/strong&gt; the cartoon was broadcast on TV. This was absolutely normal for me and all my friends back then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a final aside, the situation has changed considerably in recent times; I vividly remember being astonished in 2006 that the show &lt;em&gt;Lost&lt;/em&gt; was broadcast in French on Radio-Canada only six weeks after the original version had aired on ABC in the US. Nowadays, the lead time for dubbed versions has reduced even further. The greatest example is &lt;em&gt;Game of Thrones&lt;/em&gt;, which was available in 170 countries on the same day during its last few seasons. On the other hand, most broadcast (ie. non-streaming) media still has some lead time before the release of its dub in Québec and other international markets. Depending on the property, the French dub might be used, without a proper local Québec dub.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why am I telling you all this? &lt;a href=&quot;https://groups.google.com/g/fr.rec.anime/c/c2DdoMma9Z0&quot;&gt;Because the &lt;em&gt;Pokémon&lt;/em&gt; anime arrived in Québec only in the fall of 1999, one year after the game’s release in 1998.&lt;/a&gt;. I missed the media onslaught because there was no media onslaught. North America is not like Europe, where companies will coordinate multiple localization when releasing there. North America back then meant a strictly English release, with local Québec broadcasters left to fend for themselves. In the case of Pokémon, the translators waited a year to use the scripts from France, but dubbed the anime with Québec voice artists, using the English Pokémon name but the localized town and location names used in France. I think this is in large part because the game was only available in English in Québec; we were already familiar with names like Jynx, so French names like Lippoutou were deemed innapropriate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This made Québec the only region in the world to use the English Pokémon name in another language. Nowadays Québec has lost its local dub; the dub from France is unfortunately used, meaning that Québec is also the only region in the world where the names of the creatures suddenly changed! Lippoutou is now &lt;em&gt;de rigueur&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;are-there-more-than-150-pokémon&quot;&gt;Are There More Than 150 Pokémon?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course there have been more than 150 Pokémon for a long time, but were there more than the 150 Pokémon upon the initial release? And maybe more importantly, why does it even matter? It matters because there was indeed a hidden Pokémon, only accessible through special events or outright cheating. This created an aura of mystery around the game. Since the original Pokémon is also riddled with bugs, causing all sorts of glitches to occur, players started seeing all sort of weird things they falsely prescribed to intended secret monsters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That real hidden Pokémon was Mew, designed and hidden by Morimoto Shigeki, the programmer of the game, as a kind of prank that only he could access and share with his colleagues. Mew was, of course, mentioned in the game (Mew&lt;strong&gt;two&lt;/strong&gt; was in the game after all) but the creature was not meant to be seen. Once the rest of the team learned of the existence of Mew, they started officially distributing the creature during events. This meant it was rare for Japanese players to receive a Mew, and the interest in finding ways, real or not, to catch Mew was born. Look up the legends surrounding the truck in Vermillion City. I remember having to hear all about that truck and feeling so bad for the people who wholeheartedly believed Mew was hidden under there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mixing into this desire for the real hidden monster, the game was riddled with bugs, and bogus glitches allowed one to capture creatures that were the result of memory corruption. The most famous of these was &lt;em&gt;MissingNo.&lt;/em&gt;, and I remember schoolmates showing me the glitch all the way back in 1999. That sure didn’t help people differantiate truth from fiction; if you could catch a glitched Pokémon by surfing alongside a border of the map, why couldn’t you catch a Mew under a truck?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A year after the game’s release, idle theories and useful glitches, like the candy duplication trick, were already widely shared amongst players, even in the depths of Lac-Saint-Jean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;is-the-game-any-good&quot;&gt;Is the Game Any Good?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ve always had to bring your own fun into a &lt;em&gt;Pokémon&lt;/em&gt; title. No hand-holding can change the fact that the core games have always been about deciding on your own what’s fun for you. Do you want to create an unbeatable team? What about playing through the story with a team of six Jigglypuff? Maybe you’re interested in collecting every monster? Perhaps your interest lies in the thrill of competing against your friends? Or maybe trading with your friends? &lt;em&gt;Pokémon&lt;/em&gt; really shines when you can define an objective for yourself. I have only experienced &lt;em&gt;Pokémon&lt;/em&gt; as a solo endeavour, with the goal of completing the game, since no one cared about it when I picked it up to help me spice things up. So it was kind of boring for me. Once the Pokémon anime hit the Québec airwaves, and a group of kids at school played the game during lunch, I had moved on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you pick it up in 2022, you’ll have a tough task ahead of you; you’ll have to figure out how to have fun with that game. It’s a difficult endeavour getting harder: I mean, &lt;em&gt;Pokémon Legends: Arceus&lt;/em&gt; is right there, ready to entertain you effortlessly, albeit with terrible graphics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pokémon Legends: Arceus&lt;/em&gt; notwithstanding, every new adventure had been an improvement over the previous game, never a reinvention. So going back in time and playing the earlier titles is difficult. Perhaps if a feature you loved was removed, there was reason to walk back the route. But nostalgia is the powerful drug that keeps people coming back to the first title. When they do, those people have to contend with so many irritants. For one, the game is excruciatingly slow. Everything takes forever. You walk slow, the menus are slow, the animations are slow, the text scrolls slowly, saving is slow. Nothing is fast, and the game feels fragile as a result. It feels like you can’t push the buttons on your Game Boy too hard or the game will break under the load. Considering the game is infamous for its buggy code, I’m not surprised. After all, they famously abandoned their old code base and rewrote everything when they released their first titles on Game Boy Advance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you can get past the disrespect that game has for your time, which is a tough pill to swallow, you’ll find a quirky fun RPG with a wicked concept: no creature in the game is only an enemy. You can ultimately train and befriend your own Muk, or Lapras, or Zapdos. You can then use those monsters to trade and battle with your friends, using the connectivity afforded by the link cable. When it released, multiplayer experiences were far more niche than they are today. Online multiplayer, with services like Battle.net, were embryonic and riddled with issues and massively multiplayer online games were the purview of the committed few. Notwithstanding these advances which were all on the PC, the multiplayer concept was unique. No other game offered the ability to trade creatures with your friends. Heck, even nowadays the concept is unique, with nary a serious competitor to Game Freak in sight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only on Game Boy could Pokémon become such a large hit. The confluence of a large installed base with the ubiquity of the link cable made the gigantic hit a possibility. No other video game platform was as perfectly positioned to deliver the biggest media franchise in the world. That is what makes discussing everything around &lt;em&gt;Pokémon&lt;/em&gt; interesting for me. I don’t believe for one second that Pokémon could have happened on Super Famicom or any other console. The core idea of trading monsters with friends would have needed a technological solution that Game Freak was incapable of developing, since they were such a small studio. After 7 years of Game Boy, &lt;em&gt;Pokémon&lt;/em&gt; finally fulfilled the possibilities of the link cable. It was suddenly cool that portable consoles offered device-to-device multiplayer. Even today, the Switch is capable of playing a local game and trading monsters with another Switch next to it, without any online connectivity. You can’t do that with two PlayStations or two Xboxes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another important aspect was the incredibly long legs of the concept. You couldn’t shake the idea that sequels were inevitable while playing the first game. Exploring Kanto, you could imagine other regions with other completely different monsters just outside the realm of your Game Boy screen. It’s not a surprise that an anime, a trading card game and other video games were easily developed once Pokémon hit it big: its concept is versatile and can be adapted to almost anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, Pokémon made the Game Boy cool again, to everybody’s surprise. Game Boy hardware sales massively picked up once &lt;em&gt;Pokémon&lt;/em&gt; was released. That meant that there was a renewed interest in the console. Around the world, old Game Boy development kits were cleaned of their cobwebs, and new titles saw the light of day. With the hindsight of years of experience with the platform, and the inspiration from &lt;em&gt;Pokémon&lt;/em&gt; to innovate, the overall quality of those new games was surprising. The Game Boy went from also-ran to exciting within a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also happened to be the only console where you could make a &lt;em&gt;Pokémon&lt;/em&gt; rip-off, since no other system could allow trades between cartridges. All of that gave the Game Boy a renaissance that no console ever had, or ever will. The Game Boy was reborn thanks to those little insects walking up and down the link cable.&lt;/p&gt;

		</description>
		<link>http://localhost:4000/articles/dmg-apee/</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">dmg-apee</guid>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Dragon Warrior III</title>
		<description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;dragon-warrioriii&quot;&gt;Dragon Warrior III&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Japanese release in December 2000&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;North American release in July 2001&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Never released in Europe&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Published by Enix&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Developed by Enix &amp;amp; TOSE&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;boxart&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/cgb-bd3e/cgb-bd3e-1.png&quot; width=&quot;821&quot; height=&quot;850&quot; alt=&quot;Adventure.&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;p&gt;Adventure.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The video game discussed here was created in part by composer Sugiyama Koichi, who has publicly and financially supported historical negationism of Japanese war atrocities for decades. His vile activism should never be forgotten.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-classiest-of-the-classiest&quot;&gt;The Classiest of the Classiest&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;gb float left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/cgb-bd3e/cgb-bd3e-2.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;Game Boy Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love &lt;em&gt;Dragon Warrior 3&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Dragon Quest 3&lt;/em&gt; nowadays and in Japan upon its release). It’s a cozy pair of slippers for my soul. When I’m mentally exhausted at the end of the day, I simply sit down, put my legs up and enjoy playing this magnificent video game. I then relax by slowly unwrapping the game, step by step, battle by battle, dungeon by dungeon, town by town. It’s never too complicated or difficult, meaning I don’t have to concentrate too hard to progress, and a fatal mistake only costs half your gold. Join me, why won’t you, on this essential quest to talk about why I love &lt;em&gt;Dragon Warrior 3&lt;/em&gt; for Game Boy Color so much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;colours&quot;&gt;Colours?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to start by talking about colours. Yes, colours. I’ve heard from many people that the Game Boy Color’s palette is ugly, with muted and dull colours. I don’t think they are particularly unpleasant, but I do agree that on an original system, with its unlit display, the colours tend to wash out. Developers clearly dealt with this problem in their own way, giving lieu to a lot of games with strange choices. &lt;em&gt;Dragon Warrior 3&lt;/em&gt;’s colour choices make me feel all warm inside. I love the beautiful pairing of red and gold for the ubiquitous castle carpets. It has a very regal look that makes you feel comfortable. Whenever you stop to look at a single tile making up a wall or a ceiling, you can find small intricate details that would normally go unnoticed. It’s incredible the amount of effort that went into every corner of this game. Travelling through this chibi fantasy world is a wonderful experience. There’s always more to explore in every new town, a different corner of the map to unveil, an unseen enemy type to encounter. One reason the game is so beautiful is Toriyama Akira’s art style is perfect for a low resolution. Famously known as the creator of &lt;em&gt;Dragon Ball&lt;/em&gt;, Toriyama Akira has always been the dedicated character and creatures designer of the series. Whenever you compare his initial enemy drawings with the final result adapted for the pixellated screen of old systems, the number of retained details is impressive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the art is redrawn with such graphical constraints, you get to appreciate what makes his art style thrive here. His use of big eyes and in general large facial features while keeping a low line count is what impresses me the most. He obviously knew he was working within specific constraints and drew unique creatures that would work well with small sprites and limited colour choices. Look at his drawing of the golem, made for the first &lt;em&gt;Dragon Quest&lt;/em&gt; game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;art&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/cgb-bd3e/cgb-bd3e-3.png&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; height=&quot;700&quot; alt=&quot;Picture&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has an aggressive pose, menacingly moving towards you. It looks like a cell from an animated film. Compare that with Amano Yoshitaka’s golem from the first &lt;em&gt;Final Fantasy&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;art&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/cgb-bd3e/cgb-bd3e-4.png&quot; width=&quot;371&quot; height=&quot;447&quot; alt=&quot;Picture&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not as simple, not as iconic. You won’t find this drawing on a shirt. To be fair, I don’t think Yoshitaka had the same intention; he seems focused on making menacing monsters, readability be damned. The complicated relationship between Yoshitaka and the pixel artist for Square, Shibuya Kazuko (she often made pixel art of characters before the drawings were even made), doesn’t help consistency either. Which reinforces my point that Toriyama’s art style and methods are better suited to the Famicom’s limitations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m talking about the Famicom here because the game was originally released on that system in February 1988. Subsequently released in the US on NES in March 1992, the game is what elevated the series to its revered status in Japan. It has a four-character party, with custom-built characters with an interesting list of job options, a simple class system, and a massive world to explore. For its time, it was a tour de force that such a complicated set of features was offered in an accessible package. Other RPGs of the era were often mean with their difficulty and obtuse with their explanations. The &lt;em&gt;Dragon Quest&lt;/em&gt; games succeeded because they took pride in providing a game that was never punishing; failing at the game only ever meant losing half your gold and being transported back to your last save location. You never lose your hard-earned experience points and you’re never forced to reload a save. Because of its ease of use and lack of punishment, it’s a perfect RPG for an old curmudgeon like me who feels an urge to foolishly stay stuck in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-super-famicom-game-in-your-pocket&quot;&gt;A Super Famicom Game in Your Pocket&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game was brought to Game Boy Color in 2001, but it wasn’t the first time the game was remade for another system. In 1993, the company Heart Beat entered the fray as the new supporting developers of Dragon Quest titles, starting with a remake of &lt;em&gt;Dragon Quest III&lt;/em&gt; on Super Famicom. To understand the importance of that explanation, we need to step back and look at the development history of the series. The Dragon Quest games have a unique development structure; the trio of Horii Yuji, Toriyama Akira, and Sugiyama Koichi are responsible for their specific tasks, but the brunt of the development is done by a contracted company, initially Chunsoft. Enix (now Square Enix) ultimately publishes the games in Japan. By the time the Super Famicom became the home of the series, Chunsoft’s titles were underwhelming in many ways. The graphics were dated but more than that the user interface and speed of the games felt stuck in the past; they felt like old Famicom games. Their titles sold well, and &lt;em&gt;Dragon Quest V&lt;/em&gt; is widely regarded as a masterpiece, but it’s clear that the trio of Yuji, Akira and Koichi wanted something better. So Chunsoft was given the boot, and Heart Beat took over their role as the company developing the games. &lt;em&gt;Dragon Quest III&lt;/em&gt; on Super Famicom is the first title made by this team of developers, and I think they blew it out of the park. They lavished a ton of effort and cut no corner. Their most impressive work is undoubtedly the full attack animations for every single enemy of the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s exquisite work, seemingly drawn by another team of developers at ArtePiazza. Heart Beat introduced new dungeons to explore once you have beaten the game, along with a fun new class, the Thief, and other less successful gameplay additions we’ll broach later. It’s a masterclass in how to improve on a previously released title, and the crazy thing with the 2001 release on Game Boy Color is that every element of the Super Famicom game was brought over to the portable title, even the intricate enemy attack animations. Those animations are beautiful on Super Famicom, but they’re a notch above on Game Boy Color for the mere fact that they’re there. They took the time to redraw each and everyone of them for this Game Boy Color port.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can think of no other GBC game with such smooth animation. We have TOSE, the shadowy developer, to thank for this Game Boy Color &lt;em&gt;tour de force&lt;/em&gt;. It must have been a monumental job to redraw so many things to fit within the colour constraints of the diminutive console, and to bring over all those animations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-personal-connection&quot;&gt;My Personal Connection&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t know about any of those details when I bought the game. What had convinced me to buy the game was the poster for Nintendo Power 144, one of the first issues I read when I first subscribed to the magazine. I wanted to learn more about the upcoming Game Boy Advance and my English-reading abilities were good enough to read a game magazine by then. The poster features the cover art for the box and cartridge, a beautiful Toriyama Akira drawing, but what ultimately drew me in were all the details about the game on the back of the poster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;gallery-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;art gallery&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/cgb-bd3e/cgb-bd3e-5.jpg&quot; width=&quot;1183&quot; height=&quot;1568&quot; alt=&quot;Picture&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;art gallery&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/cgb-bd3e/cgb-bd3e-6.jpg&quot; width=&quot;1134&quot; height=&quot;1569&quot; alt=&quot;Picture&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;art gallery&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/cgb-bd3e/cgb-bd3e-7.jpg&quot; width=&quot;1114&quot; height=&quot;1569&quot; alt=&quot;Picture&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;art gallery&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/cgb-bd3e/cgb-bd3e-8.jpg&quot; width=&quot;1096&quot; height=&quot;1571&quot; alt=&quot;Picture&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s nothing more than an ad in the form of a daily journal, but I was hooked and wanted to buy the game, even though the Game Boy Advance was out by this point and I could have spent my hard-earned money on more impressive games. However, there was a problem. The only store near me that sold games, my local Zellers, did not have the game when I went there following its July release. Perhaps the Sears catalogue would carry it come the Christmas season; with the Game Boy Advance now released, I knew this was a long shot. My only chance to buy the game was seemingly gone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But by 2001, a new online store had opened, available for any resourceful 15-year old. I borrowed my parent’s credit card after much pleading, and I ordered from a new website, recently available in Canada, offering an incredible selection of merchandise and affordable shipping: amazon.ca. I do not have my order in my account anymore (I changed my Amazon account in 2004 for some reason), but &lt;em&gt;Dragon Warrior III&lt;/em&gt; was my first online purchase, way back in the prehistoric era of 2001. I still remember going to my neighbourhood’s community mailbox, and the excitement I felt at finally seeing the packages key in our family’s little mailbox. Opening the package was exhilarating. A package from the Internet. How unique! I immediately enjoyed its opening (particularly the battle between Ortega and the dragon, which feels like a Dragon Ball combat sequence), its previously mentioned colour palette, and the blazing fast walking speed. Oh man that walking speed is so sweet. You just zip through every screen at what feels like the speed of light, and I feel so grateful to the developers of the Super Famicom reissue for doing that, and for TOSE for bringing it to their Game Boy Color version. The developers valued your time, and don’t want you to waste any time uselessly. I begrudge any RPG without a quick walking speed because of this specific game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I had built a party, an interesting prospect since you’re forced to make heartbreaking class choices, you start exploring the world and discover the previously mentioned enemy animations, and the day and night cycle. It feels like nothing special, but the fact that TOSE managed to keep the Game Boy screen readable while conveying nighttime is a small feat in itself. Unfortunately, the second world map you explore much later is always in nighttime, and that’s a bummer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game is great, but not everything added with the Super Famicom reissue is perfect. I particularly take umbrage at the personality system. The initial test for your hero character’s personality is fun (particularly the unique final scenario to evaluate your reactions to a specific situation), but personalities’ numerical impact is never explained. Here’s the down-low: each personality impacts stat growth at level-up in positive or negative ways. You can gather books throughout the game to change your character’s personalities, but I would have preferred if the game was clear about what each personality did, especially since they are not equal. Two or three specific personalities are clearly better out of a large set of mostly inconsequential stuff. As it stands, nothing tells you if the personalities you find are improvements from what you have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also added Tiny Medals, unique hidden collectibles you can find and trade for increasingly better rewards. Since there is no way to precisely track which medal you already found, it can quickly become tedious to retrace your steps to look for medals you might have missed. Fortunately, you don’t need every single medal to get all the rewards, and the Thief class has two spells to alleviate your quest for the JRPG equivalent of loose change hidden between the sofa cushions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;not-hard&quot;&gt;Not Hard&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dragon Quest games have never been hard; since the very first title, the consequence for dying is merely losing half your money and being sent back to your last save location. Another gameplay element has defined the series: Magic Points are only restored by staying at an inn, outside of some rare exceptions. These two core concepts make the series favour attrition over any other sort of challenge. It’s about your party’s ability to reach the end of the dungeon before they run out of magic points, not about the particular challenge of each battle. This makes the adventure soothing and fun for me. I like playing a game to see how deep inside a cavern you can go, all while searching for treasure. Not every game needs to be a tense gauntlet like &lt;em&gt;Dark Souls&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So &lt;em&gt;Dragon Quest III&lt;/em&gt; is really fun to passively explore, as a kind of way to keep your hands busy while you relax. As a big bonus to the exploration fun, the world map is patterned after the real world; you start on an island that doesn’t exist, but then you get teleported to fake Italy and go from there. That way it’s always fun to figure out where you are compared to the real world, and what hall of mirrors parody of a nation you’ll encounter next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you enter a dungeon, you’re on your own. The game only offers a world map; you get no such luxury anywhere else. This could be a big turn off for many people, and I completely agree if you don’t want to play an RPG that doesn’t have dungeon maps, especially if it has the small viewable area of the Game Boy Color. However, the absence of a map is not always a nonstarter; great developers will adapt their design to present a cohesive map that players can learn. &lt;em&gt;Dragon Quest III&lt;/em&gt;, for the most part, offers simple dungeons that won’t be too hard to understand. Since you won’t have the crutch of a map to rely on, you’ll also learn and retain the structures of the game. After twenty years of playing, I instinctively know all the towers and caverns of the game &lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; there isn’t a map.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll still be playing &lt;em&gt;Dragon Quest III&lt;/em&gt; when I’m 80 years old, and I’ll play it on Game Boy Color, like god intended. The mobile versions have terrible redrawn sprites, and all sorts of poor choices. Please do me a favour and stay away. I cannot wrap my head around playing that game tethered to a television. I want to put on a podcast and relax in my sunroom with the game in my hands, the dog at my feet and my wife next to me. That’s my definition of heaven.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d play in bed while falling asleep, but my wife gets woken up by my button presses.&lt;/p&gt;

		</description>
		<link>http://localhost:4000/articles/cgb-bd3e/</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">cgb-bd3e</guid>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Wave Race</title>
		<description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;wave-race&quot;&gt;Wave Race&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Released in North America in July 1992&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Released in Europe in June 1997&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Never released in Japan&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Published by Nintendo&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Developed by Pax Softnica &amp;amp; Nintendo EAD&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;boxart&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/dmg-wa/dmg-wa-1.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;790&quot; alt=&quot;The neon colours and faux 3D screams early 90s. Radical, dude!&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;p&gt;The neon colours and faux 3D screams early 90s. Radical, dude!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-wunderkind-is-here&quot;&gt;The Wunderkind Is Here&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;gb float left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/dmg-wa/dmg-wa-2.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;Game Boy Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1992, Shigeru Miyamoto made his first Game Boy game with &lt;em&gt;Wave Race&lt;/em&gt;. This is important, not because &lt;em&gt;Wave Race&lt;/em&gt; is this extraordinary game; it’s actually quite ordinary. It’s important because it’s the only time Miyamoto joined a party late. Outside of &lt;em&gt;Wave Race&lt;/em&gt;, Miyamoto has been front and centre on day one with a marquee title that helps define a new system (&lt;em&gt;Donkey Kong&lt;/em&gt; on Famicom, &lt;em&gt;Super Mario World&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Super Mario 64&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Super Mario Advance&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Luigi’s Mansion&lt;/em&gt;). For the other exception, the Virtual Boy, he stayed completely away from that console and so never joined the party at all, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nintendo.co.uk/Iwata-Asks/Iwata-Asks-Nintendo-3DS/Vol-1-And-That-s-How-the-Nintendo-3DS-Was-Made/2-Shigeru-Miyamoto-Talks-Virtual-Boy/2-Shigeru-Miyamoto-Talks-Virtual-Boy-229419.html&quot;&gt;he described the Virtual Boy as a toy, not a console&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With &lt;em&gt;Wave Race&lt;/em&gt;, Miyamoto was riding in the wake of other developers instead of making the waves himself. It is a unique opportunity to see how Miyamoto works when he’s not directly collaborating with the hardware designers during the development of a console. That undeniably makes &lt;em&gt;Wave Race&lt;/em&gt; essential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conjecture&quot;&gt;Conjecture&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;gb float right&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/dmg-wa/dmg-wa-3.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;Game Boy Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why did Miyamoto start designing games for the Game Boy so late? We have no exact idea, but looking at where the Game Boy stood around 1992, we can mount a reasonable theory. With Yokoi’s R&amp;amp;D1 hard at work on project VR32, which will ultimately become the Virtual Boy, their output on Game Boy was reduced to one game a year. Hiroshi Yamauchi, Nintendo’s fearless CEO, probably decided that this was not enough games to sustain the momentum of their most successful system. Miyamoto was then asked to develop games for the system, with a third-party company assigned to work with him: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.giantbomb.com/pax-softonica/3010-5009/&quot;&gt;Pax Softnica&lt;/a&gt;. This is the same structure that was used for the development of &lt;a href=&quot;/articles/dmg-ka&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kid Icarus: Of Myths and Monsters&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, with one Nintendo employee, Masafumi Sakashita, supported by employees from a contracted company. Does Miyamoto’s collaborative effort compare favourably to Sakashita’s efforts? Yes, but both games do vastly different things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;retrogaming-in-1992&quot;&gt;Retrogaming in 1992&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;gb float left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/dmg-wa/dmg-wa-4.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;Game Boy Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most important difference between &lt;em&gt;Kid Icarus&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Wave Race&lt;/em&gt; is that Miyamoto made a backwards-looking title. The most interesting 1992 Game Boy titles are more involved experiences than this jet ski racing game. It feels more like a 1990 Game Boy title. I would have expected something with far more configurability, or with a great personality. &lt;em&gt;Super Mario Kart&lt;/em&gt;, in a sense. Instead, the game is limited in a way that makes me feel like Miyamoto was aping R&amp;amp;D1’s style. At first glance, &lt;em&gt;Wave Race&lt;/em&gt; looks like a different interpretation of &lt;em&gt;F1 Race&lt;/em&gt;, the inaugural four-player adapter title. You don’t see any charming interactions, with the game sticking close to its subject matter. The game has a save feature, but only to keep track of your time records and to tell which engine class championships you have unlocked. With the championships forcing you to redo all the races of the previous classes, this makes the game more repetitive than it ought to. Think about it, this means that whatever selection you make, you will always have to start with the same race. It’s as if a Mario Kart championship always started with the same Mario Circuit. There are two types of circuits, however, which greatly helps to shake things up. You have a racing circuit, but also a point-chasing game, where you have to go through gates to gather points. The caveat is that each gate only gives point to the first player to go through. This means you have to chase different routes than your adversaries. It’s neat, and I’m wondering if this is a racing style that exists in real life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, the game is simple, but there is that element of Miyamoto magic present, this tireless focus on core gameplay that I love so much about him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-miyamoto-touch&quot;&gt;The Miyamoto Touch&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;gb float right&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/dmg-wa/dmg-wa-5.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;Game Boy Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wave Race&lt;/em&gt; uses a top-down perspective with directional, instead of &lt;em&gt;tank&lt;/em&gt;, controls. I’ve previously discussed racing games with other perspectives, but this is our first top-down racing game. It’s very well done, with everything you need to help you succeed despite the limited point of view and constant scrolling action. You have a map with dots for the racers, helpful ranking numbers right next to your character so you don’t have to spend a moment looking away from the centre of the screen. It’s a busy game for the slow screen of the original Game Boy, but it does not cross the threshold; you can still see what’s happening. It does that by using very clean, repeating patterns for the water you race on. Even though things are blurry, you can perceive what is happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Racing on water means you can’t brake; the game uses this simple fact as the core gameplay hook of the whole game. Can you manage tight turns without brakes? The manual informs you that the best turning method is to let go of the gas as you enter the turn, use momentum to rotate your vehicle and then hit the boost right as you exit the turn to sharpen your angle. It’s fun to do. You also have to be careful to make sure you have enough boosting power for each turn, since it regenerates very slowly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;gb&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/dmg-wa/dmg-wa-6.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;Game Boy Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like the conceit of the slowly regenerating boost. It starts every race empty, and you really have to manage it. I think it’s there because your throttle is digital, and that meant that there’s no way to represent a rev-up during a turn to push your jet ski closer to the turn. By using a boost that you hit with the second button, you can mimic this precise throttling action. Surprisingly, the game has two special items, represented by animals, that give you a temporary special power. For a game with such a heavy focus on precise arcade-style racing, power-ups are an unconventional addition. But those upgrades, coupled with the funky hazards peppered throughout the race, are to me an expression of Miyamoto’s design philosophy. They make the game interesting at all times. You are never simply running in a direction, doing nothing but pressing a button. You are constantly distracted, pushed and pulled in different directions. It’s never boring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final element that keeps the game exciting at all times is the AI. It is reasonably good. They ram you when you get too close, they step in front of you to deny passage, they steal the special items, and they pull ahead of you and do not wait around if you make too many mistakes. I know they’re controlled by very simple logic, but time and effort were clearly spent to make them interesting. I can clearly see that Miyamoto sweat over their reactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until the reorganization of Nintendo divisions in 2003, Miyamoto was in the trenches developing games through the management of his own division, Nintendo EAD. Sweating over AI racers in Game Boy games. After 2003, Miyamoto took a gradual step away from managing a team, and he became this kind of internal consultant, able to provide input to his cadre of protégés who are themselves responsible for the overall management of all of Nintendo’s teams. This has made him the most senior artisan in the company, supporting every single project at the company with his insights. When Nintendo CEO Satoru Iwata suddenly died in 2015, Miyamoto even rose to the position of interim co-CEO with Genyo Takeda during the search for a replacement. The father of Mario oversaw the whole gosh darn company for years. Miyamoto is the person with the largest impact on the company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With &lt;em&gt;Wave Race&lt;/em&gt;, we have this artifact from a time where Nintendo’s most important executive wasn’t supervising the whole company’s output, and had to design a small game for a console he didn’t help to design. What an interesting legacy for such a low-key game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;art&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/dmg-wa/dmg-wa-7.jpg&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;473&quot; alt=&quot;Sold in the United Kingdom, this set included a Game Boy Pocket and two games, *Wave Race* and *Metroid II: Return of Samus*.&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sold in the United Kingdom, this set included a Game Boy Pocket and two games, &lt;em&gt;Wave Race&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Metroid II: Return of Samus&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

		</description>
		<link>http://localhost:4000/articles/dmg-wa/</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">dmg-wa</guid>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Kid Icarus: Of Myth and Monsters</title>
		<description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;kid-icarus-of-myth-and-monsters&quot;&gt;Kid Icarus: Of Myth and Monsters&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;North American release in November 1991&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;European release in May 1992&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Never released in Japan&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Published by Nintendo&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Developed by Nintendo &amp;amp; TOSE&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;boxart&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/dmg-ka/dmg-ka-1.jpg&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;637&quot; alt=&quot;They don’t make them like they used to.&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;p&gt;They don’t make them like they used to.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;not-kidding&quot;&gt;Not Kidding&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;gb float left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/dmg-ka/dmg-ka-2.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;Game Boy Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kid Icarus: Of Myth and Monsters&lt;/em&gt; can be a frustrating game. Bear in mind, playing it is not particularly frustrating. I’d argue Nintendo, collectively as a company, is the best video game developer stable in the world, so very few of their games are wholly frustrating. They have a strong company culture that focuses on exactly the right things. But games like &lt;em&gt;Kid Icarus: Of Myth and Monsters&lt;/em&gt; are expertly made but lack any valuable contributions, and that’s why I’m frustrated. The choices the game makes are pedestrian; you’re left with a bittersweet taste after completing it, never reaching the greatness you hoped for. Even though it is expertly made by &lt;a href=&quot;http://kyoto-report.wikidot.com/kid-icarus-2&quot;&gt;Nintendo with support from the shadowy TOSE&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps this development structure, of a Nintendo employee taking care of the design with TOSE delivering the programming under contract, is why I feel underwhelmed. &lt;em&gt;Metroid II: Return of Samus&lt;/em&gt; was also designed by the same person, Masafumi Sakashita, and I love that game. However, &lt;em&gt;Metroid II&lt;/em&gt; was fully designed and programmed by Nintendo R&amp;amp;D1 developers, with no outside work-for-hire. With both games designed at the same time, &lt;em&gt;Metroid II&lt;/em&gt; was clearly the primary project since they made it internally. This Game Boy sequel of &lt;em&gt;Kid Icarus&lt;/em&gt; ends up a lesser work, made with far less precious developer time. Let’s explore further the situations surrounding this lesser, but still essential, work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;an-angel-in-context&quot;&gt;An Angel in Context&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For release in the fall of 1991, Nintendo R&amp;amp;D1 had two games under development that ended up released. &lt;em&gt;Metroid II: Return of Samus&lt;/em&gt; was developed internally, while they tasked Masafumi Sakashita with supervising TOSE’s developers who were working on &lt;em&gt;Kid Icarus: Of Myth and Monsters&lt;/em&gt;. Those games are interesting for how they are both different compared to R&amp;amp;D1’s previous Game Boy titles. After the initial games released with the Game Boy in the middle of 1989, the developers at Nintendo R&amp;amp;D1 made and released &lt;em&gt;Dr. Mario&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Radar Mission&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;F-1 Race&lt;/em&gt; in 1990. Those games clearly continue in the same vein as the earliest Game Boy titles made by R&amp;amp;D1. They are simpler pick-up and play titles without any save features that can be enjoyed during quick gaming sessions. By contrast, &lt;em&gt;Metroid II&lt;/em&gt; and this second &lt;em&gt;Kid Icarus&lt;/em&gt; game are both involved exploration games with a save function. To me, this reads as a pivot for the creators of the Game Boy. Before 1991, they developed and released tailor-made experiences for a portable console. They made a new puzzle game starring Mario (that they also released on NES), they made their take on the board game &lt;em&gt;Battleship&lt;/em&gt;, and they made a small racing game showcasing a new four-player peripheral.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;gb float right&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/dmg-ka/dmg-ka-3.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;Game Boy Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With their two 1991 games, they were instead making faithful sequels to games that were made for NES, but adapted for a portable context. Moving forward, this would be the new normal on Game Boy. Case in point, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.chrismcovell.com/GameBoyDecline.html&quot;&gt;1990 was the year with the most puzzle game releases&lt;/a&gt;. Games moving forward would be more &lt;em&gt;lounging on the couch waiting for dinner&lt;/em&gt; and less &lt;em&gt;sitting in the bus waiting for your stop&lt;/em&gt;. In a sense, this is Nintendo catching up to some prescient third-party developers, who had already figured out how to make more involved games, with titles like &lt;em&gt;Double Dragon&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Ghostbusters 2&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;/articles/dmg-sa&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Final Fantasy Legend&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, Nintendo R&amp;amp;D1 would never again develop more than one Game Boy title a year after 1991. I believe their reduced output is due to their work on the Virtual Boy at the time. We know that by 1991, Gunpei Yokoi and the rest of R&amp;amp;D1 were already working on the Virtual Boy. Keep in mind, counting the cancelled games we are aware of, Nintendo R&amp;amp;D1 developers worked on at least ten games for the failed successor to the Game Boy. That’s enough to occupy a division for five years for sure. Adding on top of that the long, protracted and complicated development on the Virtual Boy itself, it’s no wonder Gunpei Yokoi and his team had little time to spare to develop Game Boy titles between 1991 and 1995. I can’t shake the feeling playing &lt;em&gt;Kid Icarus: Of Myth and Monsters&lt;/em&gt; that I’m playing a game that R&amp;amp;D1 made as a side project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another interesting aspect of the release of this &lt;em&gt;Kid Icarus&lt;/em&gt; is its North American exclusivity. The game never saw a Japanese release. With 1990’s &lt;em&gt;Balloon Kid&lt;/em&gt; also never released in Japan, 1992’s &lt;em&gt;Wave Race&lt;/em&gt; doing the same again, and &lt;em&gt;Metroid II&lt;/em&gt; releasing in North America months before hitting Japan, it seems Nintendo was somehow uninterested in its own home market. This is a bit of a mystery to me. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.neogaf.com/threads/nintendo-historical-shipment-data-1983-present.701305/&quot;&gt;The hardware sales do not support Nintendo losing interest in the Japanese Game Boy market: their numbers were strong&lt;/a&gt;. I’ve previously talked about a similar situation happening after 1998, where Nintendo released games in the US and Europe that were never released in Japan, but around 2000 the Game Boy Color hardware was selling four times faster outside Japan. This big discrepancy explains why their focus was on their growing markets between 1999 and 2001.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;gb float left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/dmg-ka/dmg-ka-4.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;Game Boy Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1991, however, the Game Boy had similar hardware sales numbers around the world, so I don’t have an easy answer as to why Japan saw so few releases from Nintendo themselves for two years. Maybe I’m missing something?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;an-angel-on-your-tv&quot;&gt;An Angel on Your TV&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s talk about the original Famicom/NES &lt;em&gt;Kid Icarus&lt;/em&gt;. I had yet to really play the original &lt;em&gt;Kid Icarus&lt;/em&gt; before I decided to write this article. It’s a bit shocking to be honest, how hard they made the game starring the little angel with a naked butt in Valentine’s Day cards. Why is the game so hard? &lt;em&gt;Kid Icarus&lt;/em&gt;’s controls are difficult to master, and all its mechanics are half-baked. Let’s discuss those sins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest one is the spawning enemies that populate the levels. Instead of each enemy being placed by the designer of the game, as in &lt;em&gt;Super Mario Bros.&lt;/em&gt;, the game simply assigns an enemy wave to discrete level segments. When the screen is scrolled within that segment, the game will always spawn the same enemy wave again and again until you scroll to the next segment. Then it will start to spawn the enemy waves that corresponds to that new segment. It makes the game more difficult because you’re always stuck facing enemies without getting a break, but more than that it’s just boring. There’s no intelligent enemy placement, it’s just wave after wave of the same enemies coming from the same directions, doing the same things over and over again. You don’t experience the artistry of a deviously placed Goomba thwarting your plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another issue is hammers. Throughout the game, you’re slowly gathering them. They’re hard to find, since they’re acquired through a two-step process, and feel precious. What do you ultimately gain with this precious resource? They give you shitty one-shot mooks during boss fights. Boo-urns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing: Let’s say you manage to survive one of these really tough gauntlets, that are also criminally boring, and you are rewarded with an upgrade. However, the game requires you to have a minimum level of life for the treasure to unlock and be usable. Don’t get confused, it’s not like the Master sword in &lt;em&gt;The Legend of Zelda&lt;/em&gt; that shoots only when at full health; you only need to hit the health threshold once to permanently unlock the upgrade. Why did they implement it that way? There’s no need for it, no reason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;gb&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/dmg-ka/dmg-ka-5.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;The Game Boy sequel unfortunately features the same boring gauntlets to receive the upgrades.&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Game Boy sequel unfortunately features the same boring gauntlets to receive the upgrades.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh and one last thing; any acquired upgrade is temporarily removed when you are in a dungeon. No increased arrow range, no defensive crystals, no nothing during the three longest game sections. Why? I think they realized the dungeons were too easy with the upgrades so they took them away. Whatever the reason for this decision, it’s just mean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;an-angel-in-your-hands&quot;&gt;An Angel in Your Hands&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a lot less egregious stuff in &lt;em&gt;Kid Icarus: Of Myth and Monsters&lt;/em&gt;. All the stuff they fixed helps this game clear a threshold, making this straightforward sequel easily enjoyable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The controls are much improved, with jumps being much more adjustable. The game also introduces a slowed-down descent (with Kid Icarus flapping his small wings) when you mash the A button.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You don’t die when you touch the bottom of the screen; the game simply scrolls in all four directions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Your upgrades work under the same system as in &lt;em&gt;The Legend of Zelda&lt;/em&gt;; they work only when you are above a certain health level, making the game more fun since you have to thread carefully.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hammers are used to acquire all sorts of stuff, making them useful to collect.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The game features a save function instead of a password system.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The text encountered in each room is in coherent English.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The game is much easier.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And best of all, enemies don’t haphazardly spawn without any artistry. Most enemies still spawn, but they spawn at a far slower pace, giving you more time to react and prepare for their attacks. They do so in a much more thoughtful manner, spawning in far smaller sections that feel much better arranged with the level layouts. This enhances the challenges you’re facing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All these small improvements highlight the important thing about &lt;em&gt;Kid Icarus: Of Myth and Monsters&lt;/em&gt;. It is a small-scale sequel without any big change to the original game’s formula. The game still has the same number of levels, the exact same structure, the same collectable upgrades, the same way to collect those upgrades. It’s commendable that they were able to adequately design the game to be brought forward to the Game Boy, but outside of this good work of translating the design of the game for a portable system while designing a sequel, the game has no inventive idea. It’s just a sequel. Let’s compare it once again to &lt;em&gt;Metroid II&lt;/em&gt;, which decided to bring forward the premise and gameplay of the first game, but focused the whole game on the devious idea that Samus Aran was hunting down Metroids to eradicate the species. They implemented new concepts to go with their premise, with a counter to indicate how many are left to kill, the creatures transforming before your very eyes, and fun twists on the game’s formula during the game’s last act.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Game Boy Essentials, I have tried &lt;a href=&quot;/articles/cgb-auhe&quot;&gt;again&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/articles/cgb-buhe&quot;&gt;again&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/articles/dmg-yt&quot;&gt;again&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/articles/dmg-adde&quot;&gt;again&lt;/a&gt; to stop people from considering a Game Boy version &lt;em&gt;just a port&lt;/em&gt; of a game. The resolution, limited colours and portable nature of the Game Boy made it difficult to simply port a title to the console. The overwhelming majority of Game Boy games usually called ports are not, since they make fundamental changes to the original game. &lt;em&gt;Kid Icarus: Of Myth and Monsters&lt;/em&gt; is no different, but boy oh boy does it make my job more difficult. An undiscerning person might quickly conclude that both games are but two sides of the same coin. Don’t make that mistake. Just play the game and see how an attentive developer with a good subcontractor can make a reasonably good game out of what was already an old-fashioned Famicom title by 1991.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s give a final shootout to TOSE that Jeremy Parish called the chameleon of game development; they’ll adapt to whatever is required, always staying invisible. In this case, I don’t think they are at fault for the slight problems of &lt;em&gt;Kid Icarus: Of Myth and Monsters&lt;/em&gt;. The people at Nintendo wanted two sprawling games for the Game Boy in 1991 that would particularly please the North American market. It’s just that this game was far less important than &lt;em&gt;Metroid II: Return of Samus&lt;/em&gt;. TOSE simply provided what was asked of them; they once again played the role of the chameleon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my next article, I want to talk about &lt;em&gt;Wave Race&lt;/em&gt;, Shigeru Miyamoto’s first foray into Game Boy development that happened the year after this game got released. That game started Miyamoto’s EAD division also releasing around one title a year for Game Boy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;gb&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/dmg-ka/dmg-ka-6.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;Damn eggplant wizards.&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;p&gt;Damn eggplant wizards.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

		</description>
		<link>http://localhost:4000/articles/dmg-ka/</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">dmg-ka</guid>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Warlocked</title>
		<description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;warlocked&quot;&gt;Warlocked&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;North American release in July 2000&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Never released in Japan&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Never released in Europe&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Published by Nintendo&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Developed by Bits Studios&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;boxart&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/cgb-bwle/cgb-bwle-1.jpg&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;644&quot; alt=&quot;Unfortunately, I don’t find the cover does this great game justice.&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I don’t find the cover does this great game justice.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;portable-marvel&quot;&gt;Portable Marvel&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;gb float left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/cgb-bwle/cgb-bwle-2.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;Game Boy Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Warlocked&lt;/em&gt; is one of the reasons I started this whole project. I always wanted to talk about it. It’s an impossible feat; a real-time strategy (RTS) game on Game Boy Color, filled to the brim with charm and delight. The game has so much gumption to achieve so much with so little that you will be filled with awe. &lt;em&gt;Warlocked&lt;/em&gt; is the quintessential essential game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lets-describe-the-game&quot;&gt;Let’s Describe the Game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Warlocked&lt;/em&gt; is obviously inspired by &lt;em&gt;Warcraft&lt;/em&gt;’s aesthetic, but it has its own artistic merit aside from its inspiration. A game clone might have some original aesthetic, but then you load a new level and everything suddenly looks like they should be sued. &lt;em&gt;Warlocked&lt;/em&gt; is not like that; it has its own style from beginning to end without falling into the pitfalls of being a clone. They copied &lt;em&gt;Warcraft&lt;/em&gt;’s premise of a fantasy RTS of Orcs fighting Humans but not much else. As an example, the orcs in Blizzard’s &lt;em&gt;Warcraft&lt;/em&gt; live in round mud houses in a rustic world of mushrooms and green water. The orcs in &lt;em&gt;Warlocked&lt;/em&gt; live in hell!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;gb&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/cgb-bwle/cgb-bwle-3.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;Game Boy Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;gb&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/cgb-bwle/cgb-bwle-4.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;Game Boy Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game is a real RTS, with a top-down view and cursor controls to order your units. It has a rudimentary control scheme, a rudimentary economy, a rudimentary tactical system. You get my point. Everything is barebones, but you cannot fault the game, it’s on Game Boy Color.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have always been a perennial RTS player, so you’ll forgive me if I speak gibberish when talking about the game. &lt;em&gt;Warlocked&lt;/em&gt; uses the first &lt;em&gt;Warcraft&lt;/em&gt; ruleset as a template. This means it has two artistically different factions that are nonetheless identical in terms of abilities. It also means that you mine two resources: gold and wood/mountain(?) in exactly the same way &lt;em&gt;Warcraft&lt;/em&gt; does it. These resources are gathered and brought back to your castle by workers. The castle is your central building that can produce more workers. In a breach of the &lt;em&gt;Warcraft&lt;/em&gt; ruleset, the central castle is already built on every map you play, and cannot be rebuilt if destroyed. It’s immediately Game Over. The fact this building cannot be built and is placed ahead of time is a limitation for the sake of simplicity. Think of every situation that &lt;strong&gt;cannot&lt;/strong&gt; happen because your main building is already placed and cannot be replicated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll talk about more details later on, but just keep in mind that the game is legitimately an RTS. You choose your campaign, go through missions that slowly teach you the concepts and in just a moment, you’re training warriors in your barracks, exploring the map, achieving objectives, defending your base, all while micromanaging your resource gathering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;gb&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/cgb-bwle/cgb-bwle-5.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;Game Boy Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surprisingly, it brings some fresh ideas to the RTS concept. First, you have dragons, the strongest units of the game and the only flying units available. They cannot be built. Instead, you find their eggs on the map, they hatch and you bring the baby dragon back to your base. The dragon matures after a short while, and you get the dragon. It basically is capture the flag with the reward being a wonderful flying unit to smite your enemies! During single player its impact is nothing fancy, but it brings some much needed tactical complexity to multiplayer matches. Oh yes indeed, the game has multiplayer and it works perfectly well! With two cartridges, you can have a ton of fun! The second idea is related to a second multiplayer mode, based around a kind-of deck building concept. Whenever you finish a single player mission, your remaining resources are put into a pool that you can use to create armies. Those armies can then be compared against other players, using the Game Boy Color’s IR port. I never was able to experience the feature since I never knew anyone who owned the game. The last idea of the game is wizards. Throughout the campaign, you will meet an assortment of unique units. They’re somewhat hidden in the maps, and once they are found they join your army, and they each bring a different spell to help you. Some have passive spells, like stronger armour for all your units, while others have active spells, like turning enemy units into chickens. They all have dumb names to accompany their spell that end in -wiz, like Chickenwiz and Quakewiz. You can have a maximum of two wizards out in battle at the same time, which means you have to choose the spells you want wisely. Once you complete a mission, if the wizard survived, they join your permanent list of wizards and they can be reused in future single-player missions. It’s obviously inspired by Pokémon, but be careful: if they die during a mission, they’re gone for good. You can replay missions to go and get them back, however. Which means you can actually have more than one copy of each wizard. Just like Pokémon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best part of the whole idea is they’re useable in multiplayer matches. So you can show off and use your wizards when playing against another player. I’ve played &lt;em&gt;Warlocked&lt;/em&gt; multiplayer matches only once in my life (thanks, Mark Weissfelner). Clowning your adversary with your wizards was the most fun I had playing this game and I only managed to do it once. Drat!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;gb&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/cgb-bwle/cgb-bwle-6.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;Game Boy Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You also need to trade your wizards if you want a full set, since you cannot acquire all the different wizards with one cartridge. The trading happens over IR, just like with the armies. I have to say, this whole IR thing is bugging me. Since the Game Boy Advance did not have this IR port, it makes it awkward to test features when you only have Game Boy Advance systems (I happen to only own one Game Boy Color at the moment). Not a fault of the game, but an unfortunate problem for this Game Boy Advance SP hoarder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;learning-about-the-game&quot;&gt;Learning About the Game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have loved &lt;em&gt;Warlocked&lt;/em&gt; from the word go. While all my friends had moved on from the Game Boy after the craze of the first &lt;em&gt;Pokémon&lt;/em&gt; game, I stayed invested in buying and playing Game Boy titles. I had always been there, really. Between 1990 and 2001, I never stopped procuring Game Boy games. By the late 90s, I was visiting the few websites I knew who covered Game Boy releases. The one website I can remember is IGN, who seemed to have assigned one person to cover the Game Boy: Craig Harris. I can remember connecting to free ISP Juno using a bugged version of its software that meant I never saw its intrusive ads (that’s a hell of a story for another time), and going on IGN to see if they had any Game Boy related news. From the first moment I heard about &lt;em&gt;Warlocked&lt;/em&gt;, I knew I had to buy that game. I hoped that my local Zellers, my only source of Game Boy games, would stock the game when it was released.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;IGN has slowly devolved to the point of inanity, but it still has articles from its heyday available if you use an external search engine to find them. I found &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ign.com/articles/2000/01/14/game-boy-in-2000&quot;&gt;two&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ign.com/games/warlocked&quot;&gt;pages&lt;/a&gt; from 2000 mentioning &lt;em&gt;Warlocked&lt;/em&gt;. Rereading those articles on IGN raises many questions about the development of the game. Why don’t I ask some of the developers?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;highlighting-the-workers&quot;&gt;Highlighting the Workers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Looking to be original on the platform is inspiring, knowing you’re breaking new ground as a developer is a key motivation, and drives you to do the hard work necessary to achieve something unique. I don’t think anyone else attempted to do what we did, the game was one of its own on the platform.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;— Dylan Beale, producer&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I gathered enough courage to reach out to Dylan Beale, the producer of the game originally from Bits Studios, to answer some of my questions. Even though we are in the midst of a pandemic unlike anything modern society has never seen, he found the time to patiently answer my questions. I feel so elated to have talked to the producer of one of my favourite games. He even, without me ever asking, roped in Steve Clark, the programmer of the game to answer my questions too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was curious about how they had the idea to make an RTS on Game Boy Color. I asked Dylan Beale how the idea for the game came about:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Dylan: People were playing a lot of &lt;em&gt;Warcraft 2&lt;/em&gt;, it was really popular amongst the staff, and naturally when you’re thinking of new game ideas you can’t help but be inspired by the games you’re loving to play at that moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m happy Dylan didn’t beat around the bush: &lt;em&gt;Warlocked&lt;/em&gt; is unapologetically inspired by &lt;em&gt;Warcraft&lt;/em&gt;. It has its own ideas, particularly with regards to the music and the gameplay, but the game proudly wears its inspirations on its sleeves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Answering the same question, Steve Clark highlighted how he was convinced of working on the project by a clever technological solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I first heard about the idea of doing an RTS for the Game Boy Color in a meeting with Foo Katan (the owner of Bits Studios) early in 1999. I’d gone in to discuss potential Game Boy Color work and he mentioned the design Martin Wheeler had been working on. He had me completely hooked by an idea for how to get around the classic &lt;em&gt;sprites on a line&lt;/em&gt; flicker issue when handling the sixteen by sixteen pixel sprites, which was to write them into the background map whenever they were suitably aligned.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;— Steve Clark, programmer&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s how you convince people that your idea is good: you elegantly solve difficult problems for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem he’s talking about his fatal to an RTS on Game Boy Color. The system cannot display more than 10 sprites on the same row across the screen. It’s a hardware limitation of its display chip, there’s no way around this. For those who don’t know, a sprite is an element that can freely move around the screen. The enemies and characters in &lt;em&gt;Mega Man&lt;/em&gt; are all made of sprites, for example, while the elements that stay solidly stuck to the background grid, like platforms and ladders, are not sprites. To further complicate things sprites are only eight by eight pixels in size on Game Boy. Most games use characters much larger than eight pixels. To make larger characters developers simply put multiple sprites next to one another to assemble characters of multiple sprites. This allows them to make characters the size they want but means the sprite limit is much tighter. In a platformer like &lt;em&gt;Super Mario Land&lt;/em&gt;, you can design your levels around the limitation. You can place enemies within your levels so the player has very few chances of encountering more than the sprite limit, amongst other things. With an RTS, you’re screwed. The player can move a large number of units wherever she likes. If the player wants to make a line full of workers that forces the console into an impossible display scenario, she can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;gb&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/cgb-bwle/cgb-bwle-7.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;Game Boy Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since every unit in &lt;em&gt;Warlocked&lt;/em&gt; is made of a grid of two sprites by two sprites, it would mean that you couldn’t display more than five units in a row. But the game is able to display five units in a row nonetheless. How is it possible? This is where Martin Wheeler’s idea comes into play. Whenever characters are immobile, they are turned into background tiles. They move from an element that can move freely around the screen to a part of the scenery. You would not be able to see this, since there is no visual difference between a sprite and a tile. The switch from one state to the other is invisible. Your units are incapable of moving separately from the background, but that’s not a problem. That’s exactly what you want anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;gb&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/cgb-bwle/cgb-bwle-8.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;You can see that when units are moving, and are therefore not tiles, you can hit the sprite limit. Here, the limit is broken and the game stops displaying the bottom half of one unit. Other games might choose to flicker the sprites. Programmers decide exactly what happens when you reach the sprite limit.&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can see that when units are moving, and are therefore not tiles, you can hit the sprite limit. Here, the limit is broken and the game stops displaying the bottom half of one unit. Other games might choose to flicker the sprites. Programmers decide exactly what happens when you reach the sprite limit.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;making-a-game-boy-color-title&quot;&gt;Making a Game Boy Color title&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve often wondered how much time a Game Boy title took to make (I guesstimate an average of six months), so I asked both of the guys what they experienced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Steve: All told the game took a little over a year from start to finish. My projects were quite varied even then, so there was no typical length as such.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Dylan: Wow, it was a long time ago. It took longer than &lt;em&gt;R-Type DX&lt;/em&gt;, but that was a port, although quite a challenging one. Creating a unique IP always requires more time, and &lt;em&gt;Warlocked&lt;/em&gt; was technically challenging with its AI pathing and having many units on the screen. We would have been driven to finish by the budget, and often having a strict timeline pushes you to make creative and technical decisions, so as a function it’s positive. What the budget did do was make the team work &lt;strong&gt;very&lt;/strong&gt; hard to get it out!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their answers are very valuable. They had budgeted for a year, and that was that, because that’s what the project needed and could afford. I don’t think many Game Boy Color titles would have a very different experience from theirs, since the Game Boy was well suited for straightforward development from the very beginning. But Dylan mentioned the challenges of bringing an RTS to Game Boy, and he gave me more insights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Dylan: The hardest programming challenges were getting the game running speedily enough, trying to ensure the AI (whether in terms of pathfinding or defending a unit’s own position) was capable enough, and, of course, multiplayer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So Dylan mentions several specific issues that he faced while developing the game, and he then quickly went into further details for each one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The enemy AI was fairly simplistic, in that the units could manage to defend themselves or choose to attack, but this simplicity allowed for the game to play quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;gb&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/cgb-bwle/cgb-bwle-9.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;Game Boy Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve talked about this before and I’ll mention it again: the Game Boy cannot do convincing AI. It just doesn’t have enough RAM and CPU speed to achieve complex enemy behaviours in real time. &lt;em&gt;Warlocked&lt;/em&gt; met the same fate: as Dylan clearly says, the AI had to be simplistic for the game to exist. In fact, the enemy AI has two behaviours:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Attacking when detecting your units&lt;/strong&gt;: When you move units within a certain range of enemy units, they will react by making a beeline to the unit who first made range and attack it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spawning units and heading towards your keep&lt;/strong&gt;: When you have been detected by specific enemy units, the pre-placed enemy barracks will start spawning units at a set rate and send them towards your keep. If they encounter one of your units or buildings, the first behaviour will trigger. Those enemy barracks are always placed in a simple path from your keep, so the path-finding is never a problem. Speaking of pathfinding:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The pathfinding was the single biggest issue in the whole game. There are many ways to program pathfinding, but they mostly rely on both a good amount of memory to determine the best route and a fast processor to cope with the computations. The Game Boy Color’s processor simply couldn’t handle some of the best algorithms for multiple units, and so a &lt;em&gt;best attempt&lt;/em&gt; system was used. Although far from perfect, it does manage to navigate itself away from a number of tricky situations, and allows units to move and act as a group with some success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be careful, dear reader, to understand the difference between enemy AI and pathfinding. While enemy AI is the behaviour of your enemy opponent, pathfinding is the movement behaviour of all the units in the game, enemy or friendly. When you click a destination on the map, it is the constant calculation of the route to take to that destination. It’s a notoriously complex computing problem, and there is no ceiling to the amount of computing power you can throw at those calculations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, I have nothing but congratulations for Dylan and the rest of the team. The path-finding is constantly stumped and fails, but it does so in a very predictable manner. Units abandon when they can’t find an entrance through a wall, and the path-finding is usually OK when you give your units a destination within the same screen. It’s when you decide to traverse large distances or turn a sharp corner that the path-finding fails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;gb&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/cgb-bwle/cgb-bwle-10.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;Game Boy Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game uses all sorts of tricks to alleviate potential path-finding issues like wood collecting. In a game like &lt;em&gt;Warcraft&lt;/em&gt;, you have to collect wood. Workers will try to collect the wood tiles that are the closest to the lumber yard. In &lt;em&gt;Warlocked&lt;/em&gt;, that was obviously too complex a behaviour to implement, so workers will simply collect wood in a straight line. It’s not ideal, but again it is a predictable behaviour that you can quickly understand and control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Multiplayer was its own special sort of challenge, and ended up using a custom master/slave mechanism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can say that with the multiplayer, they succeeded. The game runs a bit slower, and the voice clips for the units are absent in this mode, but I’d dare say multiplayer is the greatest achievement of this game. A full-fledged multiplayer RTS on Game Boy Color. I own two copies of &lt;em&gt;Warlocked&lt;/em&gt; just to be able to see it with my own eyes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An interesting quirk is that the game completely stops whenever one of the two players goes to the wizard selection screen. It’s obvious they couldn’t run both the selection screen and the game at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;gb&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/cgb-bwle/cgb-bwle-11.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;Game Boy Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-control-scheme&quot;&gt;The Control Scheme&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I asked Dylan about the challenges the game encountered, he mentioned the interface:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;From the graphics and interface side, squeezing the control system into something that used just two to four buttons and the D-Pad was something that gave me a lot of pride. Without being too fiddly, it’s possible for the player to perform a vast array of actions without having to resort to cumbersome text menus, which would break the flow of the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s quickly address the game’s user interface. The game has a small black status bar at the bottom of the screen which has all the typical RTS information. Wood/Mountain and Gold amount are always present near the corners, and the middle of the bar features contextual information. The manual is pretty clear about the status bar’s functionalities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;art&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/cgb-bwle/cgb-bwle-12.jpg&quot; width=&quot;677&quot; height=&quot;487&quot; alt=&quot;Picture&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game’s controls are fascinating. The game manages to squeeze all the barebones RTS controls into a D-Pad and four buttons. It even manages to have some surprising features: guarding another unit or building and two unit control groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The controls start and end with the cursor. Managing to move it is unfortunately the clunkiest part of the interface; a mouse is much better for this purpose, but all we have is the D-Pad. You eventually learn to get by, particularly if you learn to hold the B button to speed up your cursor speed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you have no units selected, the cursor is a big hand. Whenever you hover over a unit, you can select it using the A button. Once you have selected the unit, you can order it on the map using the A button again. Holding the A button releases your selected unit, freeing you to select another one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To train units, you simply bring the cursor over the building you wish to use, and you press A to start training. It’s easy as that. But wait a minute! There are two units that can be trained in the barracks: the warrior and the archer. How do you train two units with one button? You press A for a warrior, B for an archer when your cursor is over a barracks. They didn’t even need to implement a menu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s the minimum amount of control systems you need for an RTS. &lt;em&gt;Dune 2&lt;/em&gt;, the first significant RTS, has no functionality beyond that in terms of unit and building control. And in that game, you needed to select the movement action on the keyboard before performing it. Every time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Warlocked&lt;/em&gt; thankfully goes beyond the bare minimum. Instead of pressing the A button, if you hold it with no units selected, you can select multiple units by drawing a rectangle with the cursor. It’s now a given that an RTS will allow you to select multiple units, so you might be surprised that I’m considering this above the bare minimum, but that shit had to be invented. Like I said previously, &lt;em&gt;Dune 2&lt;/em&gt; allowed only a single unit to be selected at once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;pixel&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/cgb-bwle/cgb-bwle-13.png&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the unit selection comes with some caveats. There is no visual cue surrounding your box; it’s literally invisible. You also have a limited selection range. You cannot make a box larger than four units by four. This can be vexing; you can easily have fewer than 16 units, but spread over a much larger area than a perfect square four units wide. This makes it tiring to have to move each unit separately to fit within the small unit selection box. One thing that would help is a way to assign a control group, and what do you know, &lt;em&gt;Warlocked&lt;/em&gt; can assign two control groups? This game has a feature that &lt;em&gt;Warcraft II&lt;/em&gt; didn’t have at launch! Since you only have two buttons, and they’re already accounted for, what button are you meant to use? Select, of course. Pressing Select and holding the A or B button creates a group assigned to that button. Afterwards, pressing Select will reselect your last control group, and Select with a quick press of A or B will highlight that group for you. I have to admit I never used the feature when I initially got the game as a teenager; the part where you have to hold Select to create a group always stumped me. Any units can be ordered to guard and follow any other unit or building. This is what I used to allow me to move large groups of units instead. It was clunkier, but that’s all I knew how to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final order of business in the game is the worker. How do you build structures when all the buttons are so overloaded with functionality? The game reuses the B button and it works OK. Whenever you have workers selected, the game will display a construction overlay on the ground automatically. Pressing the B button will present a small menu in the status bar, where you can choose which building to build with the D-Pad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;gb&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/cgb-bwle/cgb-bwle-14.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;Game Boy Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once that’s done, you’re good to go; your workers will take care of the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-music&quot;&gt;The Music!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;gb float right&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/cgb-bwle/cgb-bwle-15.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;Game Boy Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I implore you to listen to the soundtrack of &lt;em&gt;Warlocked&lt;/em&gt;. The soundtrack is made by a composer known for his Commodore 64 work, Jeroen Tel, and it has that wonderful &lt;em&gt;European composer&lt;/em&gt; quality that is so powerful on Game Boy. It has this interesting emotional undercurrent that really elevates the whole game, with my favourite tracks &lt;em&gt;Lava 1&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Woods 1&lt;/em&gt;. I think I get this feeling because the game is trying something different from the usual understated Game Boy music. RTS music tends to be very preeminent; there’s a strong tradition in the genre of the music never taking a step back during gameplay. I guess we have Frank Klepacki, composer of Westwood titles, to thank for his active soundtracks. &lt;em&gt;Warlocked&lt;/em&gt; seems to be going in the same direction of an energetic soundtrack that draws attention to itself, by taking inspiration from &lt;em&gt;Warcraft 2: Tides of Darkness&lt;/em&gt;. The soundtrack in that game is unforgettable and grabs your attention immediately. &lt;em&gt;Warlocked&lt;/em&gt; goes for the same effect, on a Game Boy Color, and &lt;strong&gt;I love it&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I first bought the game as a teenager in 2000, I would start the music test on a track I liked, connect headphones to my Game Boy Color, put it in my pockets and walk to school listening to the music. I liked it that much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to thank Dylan Beale and Steve Clark for their insights into the game. I did not feature every single quote they gave me in this article, but I learned a lot from their openness. They’re the first Game Boy developers I talked to, and I could never have hoped for a better duo. Thank you guys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I guess I also have to thank them for making &lt;em&gt;Warlocked&lt;/em&gt;! This game is such a wonderful curiosity, and it couldn’t have happened without all the developers’ sheer force of will. They made an RTS on Game Boy Color. And it’s not bad, far from it. You owe it to yourself to play it, it’s essential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;gb&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/cgb-bwle/cgb-bwle-16.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;Game Boy Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

		</description>
		<link>http://localhost:4000/articles/cgb-bwle/</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">cgb-bwle</guid>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>3D Pocket Pool</title>
		<description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;3d-pocket-pool&quot;&gt;3D Pocket Pool&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;European release in March 2001&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Never released in North America&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Never released in Japan&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Published by Virgin Interactive&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Developed by Aardvark Software&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;boxart&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/cgb-bvpp/cgb-bvpp-1.jpg&quot; width=&quot;488&quot; height=&quot;500&quot; alt=&quot;The game features a photograph for the cover but uses very stylized art in the game.&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;p&gt;The game features a photograph for the cover but uses very stylized art in the game.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;too-late-for-pool&quot;&gt;Too Late for Pool&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;gb float left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/cgb-bvpp/cgb-bvpp-2.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;Game Boy Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This game feels like it’s coming from another planet! &lt;em&gt;3D Pocket Pool&lt;/em&gt; is this strange experience that you can’t quite put your finger on. It would also be somewhat charming if not for all its problems. Let’s look together at this off-kilter game, and figure out why it’s essential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;obscure-release&quot;&gt;Obscure Release&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;3D Pocket Pool&lt;/em&gt; was released only in Europe in 2001, during the twilight of the Game Boy Color when everybody was waiting for the Game Boy Advance. The GBA would be unleashed upon the world merely two months later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During this era I was still playing my Game Boy Color and I missed a bunch of games because I was waiting for the GBA. So anytime I see a game from around March 2001, when Nintendo unveiled the GBA price and launch games, I can’t dissociate the game from the excitement I had for the upcoming Game Boy Advance. Games like &lt;em&gt;Magi Nation&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Oracle of Seasons&lt;/em&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;em&gt;Oracle of Ages&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Alone in the Dark: The New Nightmare&lt;/em&gt;. Those games, and many more, saw their release overshadowed by the Game Boy Advance. And this time Europe, usually a laggard when it came to releases, was waiting at the same time as the rest of the world. Nintendo had announced the release of the Game Boy Advance in Europe a mere 11 days after North America.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;3D Pocket Pool&lt;/em&gt; was released within this era. So what would have been an obscure release on a good day (come on, it’s a pool game) was even more obscure because it was a Europe-only game for a console way past its bedtime. The developer, British-based Aardvark Software, had clearly gone downhill. You can find information about a reasonable amount of games they made in the 80s for British computers, but once you hit the 90s they seem to have made only two games: a port of &lt;em&gt;Duke Nukem 3D&lt;/em&gt; for PlayStation in 1997 and &lt;em&gt;3D Pocket Pool&lt;/em&gt; in 2001. Something is afoot. With the scope of &lt;em&gt;3D Pocket Pool&lt;/em&gt;, I wouldn’t be surprised if it was made by one or two people with little to no connection to Aardvark Software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How obscure can this game be? What about this: it’s the type of game that’s often missing from Game Boy Color romsets. It’s probably because it was not released in North America and Japan that the game is missed. More obscure than that, you’re on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.unseen64.net&quot;&gt;Unseen64&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;addams-family-pool&quot;&gt;Addams Family Pool&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3D is in the title; it’s the reason this game exists. I doubt a top-down pool game would have been able to secure a release in 2001. However, a game with a hook could perhaps be different enough to sell. It seemingly didn’t, as it never left Europe. Make no mistake: other simple games with a hook were released at that time. Simpler titles unattached to a licence that harkened back to the early years of the Game Boy were still released up to the end of 2001. &lt;em&gt;Trouballs&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Puzzled&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Ultimate Surfing&lt;/em&gt; are other titles from this period I could quickly find. It’s not a lot, since the Game Boy Color library by then was mostly made up of licensed adaptations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;gb float right&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/cgb-bvpp/cgb-bvpp-3.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;Game Boy Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of simplicity, &lt;em&gt;3D Pocket Pool&lt;/em&gt; is no more complicated than 1990s &lt;em&gt;Side Pocket&lt;/em&gt;. Outside of the whole 3D conceit, it’s actually a simpler game. So what about that whole 3D thing? How is it possible? The game uses the exact same trick used by &lt;a href=&quot;/articles/cgb-bt5e&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Toy Story Racer&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Pre-rendered backgrounds are drawn to simulate a 3D pool table, and a sprite is used over the 3D image for each ball. A shadow effect underneath each ball is accomplished by using a flickering black sprite. The same flickering is used for the ball trajectory that appears when you line up your shot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I kind of appreciate the gameplay because it has zero randomness. When you are lining up a shot, if the trajectory that appears shows your target going into the pocket it will always go in the pocket. It achieves this because it has no three-click system like a golf game that requires precise timing on your part. I discussed the three-click system in my &lt;a href=&quot;/articles/cgb-awxe&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mario Golf&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; article. Instead, you manually select the strength of your shot. By eliminating any sort of twitchy response from the game, it becomes a game about geometry. Can you figure out the angles required to put the balls in the pockets? However, the fun you can have when figuring out shots is severely limited by the poor simulation and camera controls. The game is also slow to operate and imposes a timer to shoot when you are playing the tournament mode. This all but ensures you will never have enough time to find a working angle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;gb&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/cgb-bvpp/cgb-bvpp-4.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;The AI is thinking in this screenshot. You can see the thought bubbles on the top right.&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;p&gt;The AI is thinking in this screenshot. You can see the thought bubbles on the top right.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the game has an AI that is extremely slow to act. Whenever its turn comes up, it takes a long time before it shoots. You see a little thought bubble above your adversary, indicating that the character is thinking. It must be calculating a valid shot, and it takes its sweet ass time to do so. It often takes more time than you are allowed. They never even bothered showing a timer for the AI. They clearly knew their AI couldn’t respond quickly, so they simply let it work without a time constraint. It means you spend more time waiting for your adversary to act than actually playing the game yourself. It kills any hope of enjoyment you could have gotten from this obscure title.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;music&quot;&gt;Music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do you know a Game Boy title was developed in Europe? The noise channel is used for the melody of the music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;funky-people&quot;&gt;Funky People&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;gb&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/cgb-bvpp/cgb-bvpp-5.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;Game Boy Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The game has this tattoo parlour vibe for its cast of characters. I wouldn’t be surprised to find those weird looking drawings on a trucks’ mud flap. All the women characters have terribly sexist descriptions on the character select screen. You’re also stuck looking at their dumb faces for the whole time you’re playing. To pretend like you’re playing pool with someone, they do this dumb thing where they will flip the table before your opponent plays, and change the character art above the fold to them hitting the ball. So if you pay attention and think hard about what they’re trying to do, you too can figure out why they rotate the camera every time your adversary shoots the ball.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;3D Pocket Pool&lt;/em&gt; is seemingly an echo of Aardvark’s own 1989 game &lt;em&gt;3D Pool&lt;/em&gt;. The game, released on Commodore’s Amiga, billed itself as the first 3D pool game. I’ve watched a quick video of the Amiga game and it seems making a responsive pool game was beyond the hopes and dreams of the developers, in 1989 as well as 2001. That some people, somewhere in England, bothered to make a bad pool game for Game Boy Color in 2001 is fascinating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;gb&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/cgb-bvpp/cgb-bvpp-6.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;The game switches to a top-down view upon pressing Select. It just serves to show how the game is even less complex than *Side Pocket*, a game from way back in 1990.&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;p&gt;The game switches to a top-down view upon pressing Select. It just serves to show how the game is even less complex than &lt;em&gt;Side Pocket&lt;/em&gt;, a game from way back in 1990.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

		</description>
		<link>http://localhost:4000/articles/cgb-bvpp/</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">cgb-bvpp</guid>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Donkey Kong Land 2</title>
		<description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;donkey-kong-land2&quot;&gt;Donkey Kong Land 2&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;North American release in September 1996&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Japanese release in November 1996&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;European release in November 1996&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Published by Nintendo&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Developed by Rare&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;boxart&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/dmg-adde/dmg-adde-1.jpg&quot; width=&quot;1480&quot; height=&quot;1478&quot; alt=&quot;An exciting cover for an unfortunate sequel.&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;p&gt;An exciting cover for an unfortunate sequel.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ape-escape&quot;&gt;Ape Escape&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;gb float left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/dmg-adde/dmg-adde-2.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;Game Boy Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My article on &lt;a href=&quot;/articles/dmg-yt&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Donkey Kong Land&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is by far my most popular. It’s the one that has received the most feedback; from book reviews on Amazon, from Reddit’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://old.reddit.com/r/gameboy&quot;&gt;/r/gameboy&lt;/a&gt;, from talking to my friends. With that in mind, I should feel a certain responsibility discussing &lt;em&gt;Donkey Kong Land 2&lt;/em&gt;. I don’t since they barely changed anything, it’s just the same core mistakes all over again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the first game, I had decades of experience to share; I owned the game has a kid. This time, I bought the game as an adult, specifically for this project. Since I have never played the game before, it means my opinions are fresh. The game features only minuscule improvements on the issues I had with the first game, so I am disappointed to say I do not like this sequel. It stings particularly because this game tries to reproduce &lt;em&gt;Donkey Kong Country 2: Diddy’s Kong Quest&lt;/em&gt; for the Game Boy, and I simply adore &lt;em&gt;Donkey Kong Country 2&lt;/em&gt;. I have fond memories of playing the game with my best friend from primary school, slowly inching our way, level by level, through this difficult Super Nintendo classic. &lt;em&gt;Donkey Kong Land 2&lt;/em&gt; attempts to ape this seminal game and fails miserably. At least the first &lt;em&gt;Land&lt;/em&gt; game had original levels. Essentially, we’re faced here with the harsh fact that a bad adaptation of a great game is worse than a bad original work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;slightly-better-on-the-eyes&quot;&gt;Slightly Better on the eyes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest issue with the first &lt;em&gt;Donkey Kong Land&lt;/em&gt; is its inscrutable backgrounds that make everything blurry. The developers of &lt;em&gt;Donkey Kong Land 2&lt;/em&gt; thought so too; the second game has somewhat cleaner backgrounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;gallery-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;gb gallery&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/dmg-adde/dmg-adde-3.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;Game Boy Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;gb gallery&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/dmg-adde/dmg-adde-4.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;Game Boy Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;gb gallery&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/dmg-adde/dmg-adde-5.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;Game Boy Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;gb gallery&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/dmg-adde/dmg-adde-6.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;Game Boy Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They evidently tried to alleviate the problem by using more whitespace but I think they were trying to improve a fundamentally flawed concept. There is no way to make 3D designs work flawlessly on the original Game Boy screen, no matter how much whitespace you’re leaving in the background. They did not fully commit to the improvements; you still have many decorative elements that crush visibility throughout the game. You can better discern the position of the dark blobs that populate the screen, but you’ll have a hard time figuring out what those blobs are supposed to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Is this a background element or an enemy? It threw what looks like a barrel, so I guess it’s an enemy? Oh, it wasn’t a barrel, it was a cannonball so now I’m dead. Why don’t I play some &lt;em&gt;Kirby’s Dream Land 2&lt;/em&gt; instead of this crap?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You need the clean lines of hand-drawn pixel art to give you a game you’ll be able to see without issues. Since the whole marketing angle of the &lt;em&gt;Donkey Kong Country&lt;/em&gt; series was its use of 3D graphics, they chose to use the same underlying technique on Game Boy. To hell with the game’s quality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pocket-reinvention&quot;&gt;Pocket Reinvention&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;gb float right&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/dmg-adde/dmg-adde-7.png&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; alt=&quot;Game Boy Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just like &lt;em&gt;Donkey Kong Land&lt;/em&gt; was released to coincide with the arrival of the Super Game Boy on store shelves, &lt;em&gt;Donkey Kong Land 2&lt;/em&gt; was released on the same day as the Game Boy Pocket. If we are supposed to understand that this game was made with the Game Boy Pocket in mind, I guess it solves its more egregious graphical issues, but we still must acknowledge all the poor players who did not own a Game Boy Pocket to play this bad game. I had to contend with my trusty grey brick until I bought a Game Boy Color in 2000, and I was not alone. For seven years the Game Boy had been sold to most everyone who wanted a Game Boy when the Game Boy Pocket was introduced in 1996. The Pocket did not sell particularly well nor change the Game Boy market significantly. It also raised the sale price of the Game Boy by $10 USD upon release. How come Nintendo improved their initial design only by 1996? Because during four of those seven years, Yokoi Gunpei and R&amp;amp;D1 were busy working on the Virtual Boy. Once they finally abandoned it on the market in 1995, Yokoi finally tasked his team with building a better Game Boy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;art&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/dmg-adde/dmg-adde-8.jpg&quot; width=&quot;2000&quot; height=&quot;2000&quot; alt=&quot;Picture&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That the Game Boy Pocket came as the amends for the sins of Virtual Boy makes sense. Since their previous creation was too much of an overreach, they went in the opposite direction and the Game Boy Pocket is the safest redesign possible. Its marquee feature is the improved display, finally breaking from the shackles of the iconic green screen. The Game Boy Pocket still uses a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Super-twisted_nematic_display&quot;&gt;super-twisted nematic LCD&lt;/a&gt; with all its faults, but it is much improved, with far less ghosting and true shades of grey. They also made the screen slightly bigger in physical size while keeping the same resolution. The screen has no light source, but that was still par for the course for a device sold for $70 USD in 1996. The overall device size is smaller, with a fresh, timeless design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;art float right&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/dmg-adde/dmg-adde-9.jpg&quot; width=&quot;1512&quot; height=&quot;2016&quot; alt=&quot;Picture&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They were also able to only require two batteries, since between the release of the DMG in 1989 and the Pocket in 1996, a small revolution happened in the world of consumer electronics: the move from 5 V to 3 V. &lt;a href=&quot;https://nerdlypleasures.blogspot.com/2014/10/battery-life-in-8-bit-game-boy-line.html&quot;&gt;The crew at Nintendo R&amp;amp;D1 were able to make the Pocket work with 3 V&lt;/a&gt;, meaning that instead of the four batteries needed to reach 5 V (a single AA battery provides a nominal 1.5 V), you only needed two batteries to reach 3 V. On the negative side, they chose to use AAA batteries, which dropped the battery life of the Pocket to the 10-hour mark, while the original DMG usually gave you 20 hours of gameplay with its AAs. No other Game Boy would ever use the diminutive AAA batteries again, and they would all offer more than 10 hours of battery life. All that to say that &lt;em&gt;Donkey Kong Land 2&lt;/em&gt; had at its disposal a device better suited for its visuals, but it still doesn’t make the game good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bad-as-a-portable-donkey-kong-country2&quot;&gt;Bad as a Portable Donkey Kong Country 2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might be tempted to say: “Pierre-Luc, the first game was just a bizarre adaptation with original levels and areas. This time, they just ported &lt;em&gt;Donkey Kong Country 2&lt;/em&gt;, so it must be good?” Before I tell you that you’re unfortunately wrong, I wish to define one word in your sentence, the word &lt;strong&gt;port&lt;/strong&gt;. What is a port? Let’s define it by peeling the onion of &lt;em&gt;DKL2&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first layer, the marketing of the game, is indeed different from the Super Nintendo game. It has a different name, uses different images to promote itself. But it is irrelevant, since a port is not defined by its appearance outside the software that makes the game. We already established previously that &lt;a href=&quot;articles/cgb-buhe&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Heroes of Might &amp;amp; Magic&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on Game Boy Color was not a port simply because it reused the same name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second layer, once the game is played, is the world map. It is strikingly similar to the original game. The second and third areas have been merged, inside each area you have small changes here and there, and the world map is for some reason mirrored, but we do not have something that would disqualify this game as a port.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the third layer, once you play a level, the game style and controls are nearly the same. We have a platform game with the same overall controls, with some concessions made for the four-button difference between both consoles. Gone is the team-up move, which allowed a Kong to stand on the shoulder of the other one to reach higher platforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s at the fourth layer, the level layouts, that we reach the unequivocal truth that we are not playing a port, since every single level is different from the SNES game. They usually have the same theme as their SNES versions. One level is about using barrels to navigate vines, another level features jumping on reeds in a swamp. But every level is different; they’re dumbed-down echoes of the SNES levels. They’re meant to confuse you by looking like the Super Nintendo original levels. This highlights a fundamental truth that applies to &lt;strong&gt;so many Game Boy games&lt;/strong&gt;: unless the original environmental resolution is maintained, a game cannot be a port. Puzzle games like &lt;a href=&quot;/articles/dmg-tr&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tetris&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/articles/dmg-apce&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mario’s Picross&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Dr. Mario&lt;/em&gt; require fewer pixels to function than the Game Boy has, so they can be ports. Turn-based games like &lt;em&gt;Game Boy Wars&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Dragon Warrior I &amp;amp; II&lt;/em&gt; can scroll and offer menus to display the same amount of data, so they can be ports (the &lt;em&gt;Game Boy Wars&lt;/em&gt; games were original titles but it’s just an example). Point-and-click adventure games like &lt;em&gt;Shadowgate&lt;/em&gt; redraw their environments, but change nothing about their original structure so they also work. &lt;em&gt;Super Mario Bros. Deluxe&lt;/em&gt; is indeed a port, since they didn’t change the levels or Mario’s jumping to fit within the screen. Finally, a great example is &lt;em&gt;DuckTales&lt;/em&gt;. Most mentions of the Game Boy version call it a port, but it is not. It looks awfully similar to the NES game, but &lt;strong&gt;a lot&lt;/strong&gt; has been changed in the levels to make the game possible on the portable system. This is the same with &lt;em&gt;DKL2&lt;/em&gt;. Most people will call it a port, but it is definitely not a port because of the irreconciliable level differences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now that we’ve established that it is not a straight port, but a reimagining of &lt;em&gt;DKC2&lt;/em&gt;, I can tell you the decisions they made to reimagine the classic SNES game are horrible. I won’t go into too much detail, but suffice it to say they made an easier, shorter and way less interesting game. Levels in &lt;em&gt;DKC2&lt;/em&gt; have this delicious forward momentum. You always want to unfold the next challenge. For example, in Kannon’s Klaim, the second level of the second world is filled with Krocs that shoot barrels or cannonballs. You&amp;#8217;re climbing up the mine shaft, and you’re constantly bombarded by new challenges using those same enemies. It’s fun to discover the designers’ next idea.  On Game Boy, they’ve all been taken out. The adaptation of this level is just a repetition of Auto Fire Barrels over and over until the end of the level where you have one crocodile with a cannon. They only put one signature enemy of the level! I think they removed those enemies because they were too hard to see on the Game Boy screen, which meant they took at all the fun out of the level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole game is like that. The first world on SNES, the pirate boat, is this fun, easy world with lots of secrets hidden all over the place. They took out the exploration and fun secrets on Game Boy. The third world is this swamp with interesting jumping challenges on SNES. The levels that survived the transition to Game Boy are just boring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most exciting section of &lt;em&gt;Donkey Kong Country 2&lt;/em&gt; is Kremland, a deadly amusement park interspersed with beehives. It’s this tough area with most levels featuring exciting new play styles. There are two similar roller coaster levels and they went so far has to give them two different control styles; one has the Kong jump from the cart and the other has the cart itself jump. On the other hand, the Game Boy’s Kremland area is just boring. I stopped playing as I reached the Kremland area on Game Boy. I cannot believe that the developers at Rare suddenly became good at porting their own game. Their first two levels were simply too bad for me to warrant any more of my time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;once-again-saddled-with-a-terrible-camera&quot;&gt;Once Again Saddled With a Terrible Camera&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My limited time with the game allowed me to confirm that the camera is still problematic. The game features the same twitchy camera that I hated so much with the first game. My camera experimentation also allowed me to discover another issue I have with this game. The second level of &lt;em&gt;DKC2&lt;/em&gt;, Mainbrace Mayhem, is actually a personal favourite. It’s set on the pirate ship’s sails and I love it because you never get confused about where to go next in this vertical level that you navigate in a seesaw pattern. It does this by locking the camera’s vertical scrolling; you can’t make it scroll any higher by jumping when there is another section of the level above you. You can sometimes break that mechanism by jumping much higher than you normally would, but it is surprisingly effective at guiding you towards your destination without confusing you. It’s not perfect, but it works surprisingly well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;DKL2&lt;/em&gt; works the same way, but the level structure is more cramped, so you often jump and see level elements to the sides. You start wondering where you are supposed to go, and can easily skip whole sections of the level simply because you saw a space much later in the level you could reach. It’s great if you want to quickly get through a level, but terrible in a design sense. This is a common occurrence with this game: it tries to ape the SNES game but does it in a bad way which causes confusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;saving--batteries&quot;&gt;Saving &amp;amp; Batteries&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s take a final moment to discuss something tangentially related to this game: batteries. My cartridge of &lt;em&gt;Donkey Kong Land 2&lt;/em&gt; had a dead battery, so I had to change it. The way to know a battery is dead is your save gets deleted the second you turn off your Game Boy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saves on cartridge games work with a watch battery hidden inside the cartridge that keeps a small dedicated section of RAM powered without interruption for decades. If this small RAM section is without electricity, your saves are gone. It sounds crazy but it works. The battery is not getting recharged while the console is powered on either; watch batteries are non-rechargeable. It just works for decades without issues. It can stay powered on for so long because a watch battery can last a very long time if it only needs to power some small circuitry without a display.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;art&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/dmg-adde/dmg-adde-10.jpg&quot; width=&quot;1512&quot; height=&quot;1423&quot; alt=&quot;Picture&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you buy original Game Boy cartridges in this day and age, you will eventually encounter a cartridge that no longer keeps your saves. However, if you decide to change a game’s battery yourself, here are some pieces of advice:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Buy the specific screwdriver you need to open a Game Boy cart. Do not fall for that melted pen &lt;em&gt;trick&lt;/em&gt;, it’s a terrible idea that always ends in a mess.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You don’t necessarily need to de-solder the battery connectors. I use a box cutter and patience to cut the very little bit of solder on the battery.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t hesitate to use a slightly bigger battery. I use CR2032 batteries since they’re so easy to find, and they also help with my final tip.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use electric tape to hold the battery snugly between the original connectors. Since I use bigger batteries, the cartridge’s plastic housing also squeezes the battery in place.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;art&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/dmg-adde/dmg-adde-11.jpg&quot; width=&quot;1512&quot; height=&quot;1605&quot; alt=&quot;Picture&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, don’t repeat my rookie mistake; don’t put the battery on backward and then think the cartridge itself is broken. I had done that and was convinced my cartridge was screwed. I finally realized my mistake after an embarrassing amount of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel like I talked about everything around &lt;em&gt;Donkey Kong Land 2&lt;/em&gt; instead of talking about this forsaken game. I did all that for good reasons, since there is not a lot to talk about. The game is slightly better than the first one, but it still is fundamentally broken. The people at Rare could have easily redesigned the core concept, but they instead just made the same mistakes again. They probably believed that adapting SNES levels and lowering the number of details in the backgrounds would be enough to improve their concept. They were wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I guess it proves that the developers at Rare never lost their roots as developers of flawed games. They made interesting games before &lt;em&gt;Donkey Kong Country&lt;/em&gt;, when they were originally Ultimate Play the Game and afterwards as Rare. Their games usually had some sort of fatal flaw that made them impossible to love. &lt;em&gt;Battletoads&lt;/em&gt; like most of their games was way too hard. &lt;em&gt;A Nightmare on Elm Street&lt;/em&gt; was too complicated for its own sake. &lt;em&gt;Wizards &amp;amp; Warriors&lt;/em&gt; had floaty controls ill-suited for the levels in the game. When they started collaborating directly with Nintendo, however, they started making flawless titles. They also severely slowed down and stopped releasing a dizzying amount of games. They still had it in them to make a bunch of clunkers, it seems.&lt;/p&gt;

		</description>
		<link>http://localhost:4000/articles/dmg-adde/</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">dmg-adde</guid>
	</item></channel>
</rss>